<act><tid>988937</tid>
<title>THE INTERNATIONAL AIRPORTS AUTHORITY ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 43 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 8th December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of an authority for the 
management of certain aerodromes whereat international air transport 
services are operated or are intended to be operated and for matters 
connected therewith.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>126114</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, commencement and application.
<section><tid>576408</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the International Airports Authority Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>604190</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>1742592</tid>
<number>3</number>It applies, in the first instance, to the aerodromes of 
Bombay (Santa Cruz), Calcutta (Dum Dum), Delhi (Palam) and Madras 
 (Meenambakkam) and the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, apply the provisions of this Act to any other 
areodrome whereat international air transport services are operated or 
are intended to be operated and with effect from such date as may be 
specified in the notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1976188</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>741191</tid>
<number>a</number>" airport" means an areodrome as defined in clause (2) of 
section 2 of the Aircraft Act, <year>1934</year> (22 of <year>1934</year>) and 
to which this Act applies or is made applicable;

</section>

<section><tid>665967</tid>
<number>b</number>" airstrip" means an area used or intended to be used for 
the landing and take- off of aircrafts with short take- 
off and landing characteristics and includes all 
buildings and structures thereon or appertaining 
thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1862659</tid>
<number>c</number>" Authority" means the International Airports Authority 
of India constituted under section 3;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>60</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 2- <year>1972</year>: vide Notification No. S. O. 87 (E), dated 1- 2- <year>1972</year>. 
Published in the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II Sec. 3 (ii), 
p. 225.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1461474</tid>
<number>d</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>763452</tid>
<number>e</number>" heliport" means an area, either at ground level or 
elevated on a structure, used or intended to be used 
for the landing and take- off of helicopters and 
includes an area for parking helicopters and all 
buildings and structures thereon or appertaining 
thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>384494</tid>
<number>f</number>" member" means a member of the Authority and includes 
the Chairman but for the purposes of sections 4, 5, 6 
and 7 does not include the ex officio member referred 
to in clause (b) of sub- section (3) of section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1928715</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1554237</tid>
<number>h</number>" regulations" means regulations made under this Act.
CHAP

THE INTERNATIONAL AIRPORTS AUTHORITY OF INDIA

CHAPTER II

THE INTERNATIONAL AIRPORTS AUTHORITY OF INDIA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1826699</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and incorporation of the Authority.
<section><tid>1382280</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from the commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall 
constitute an authority to be called the International Airports 
Authority of India.

</section>

<section><tid>395397</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid 
having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the said name 
sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1745242</tid>
<number>3</number>The Authority shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1358331</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1945791</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director- General of Civil Aviation, ex officio; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452252</tid>
<number>c</number>not less than six and not more than thirteen members to 
be appointed by the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>709534</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairman shall be a whole- time member and the other 
members referred to in clause (c) of sub- section (3) may be appointed 
as whole- time or part- time members as the Central Government may think 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>225172</tid>
<number>5</number>The names of persons appointed as members shall be notified 
by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>61</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>13796</tid>
<number>6</number>During the temporary absence of the Chairman, the Central 
Government may appoint another member to act as the Chairman.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>888003</tid>
<number> 4</number> Disqualification for office of member. A person shall be 
disqualified for being appointed as a member if he--
<section><tid>700116</tid>
<number>a</number>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an 
offence, which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, involves moral turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>324916</tid>
<number>b</number>is an undischarged insolvent; or

</section>

<section><tid>1752811</tid>
<number>c</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent 
Court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1323028</tid>
<number>d</number>has been removed or dismissed from the service of the 
Government or a corporation owned or controlled by the 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>119925</tid>
<number>e</number>has, in the opinion of the Central Government, such 
financial or other interest in the Authority as is 
likely to affect prejudicially the discharge by him of 
his functions as a member.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1131705</tid>
<number> 5</number> Term of office and conditions of service of members.
<section><tid>280277</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of section 6, every member shall hold office 
for a period of three years from the date on which he assumes office:
Provided that the Central Government may--


<subsection><tid>1240651</tid>
<number>a</number>terminate the appointment of any whole- time member, who 
is not a servant of the Government, after giving him 
notice for a period of not less than three months or in 
lieu thereof on payment of an amount equal to his 
salary and allowances, if any, for a period of three 
months;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>142679</tid>
<number>b</number>terminate the appointment of any part- time member who is 
not a servant of the Government after giving him notice 
for such period as may be prescribed; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1069461</tid>
<number>c</number>terminate at any time the appointment of any member who 
is a servant of the Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>87245</tid>
<number>2</number>The other conditions of service of the members shall be such 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1726351</tid>
<number>3</number>Any member may resign his office by giving notice in writing 
for such period as may be prescribed to the Central Government and,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>62</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

on such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that 
Government, such member shall be deemed to have vacated his office.


</section>

<section><tid>1538670</tid>
<number>4</number>A casual vacancy caused by the resignation of a member under 
sub- section (3) or otherwise may be filled by fresh appointment and 
the person so appointed shall hold office for the remaining period for 
which the member in whose place he is appointed would have held 
office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1697120</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vacation of office of member. The Central Government shall 
remove a member if he--
<section><tid>1726082</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 4:
Provided that no member shall be removed on the ground that 
he has become subject to the disqualification mentioned 
in clause (e) of that section, unless he has been given 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter; 
or


</section>

<section><tid>1219340</tid>
<number>b</number>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or

</section>

<section><tid>1637710</tid>
<number>c</number>is, without obtaining leave of absence from the 
Authority, absent from three consecutive meetings of 
the Authority; or

</section>

<section><tid>286671</tid>
<number>d</number>in the opinion of the Central Government, has so abused 
his position as to render his continuance in office 
detrimental to the public interest:
Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause 
unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard in the matter.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1182224</tid>
<number>7</number>Eligibility of member for re- appointment. Any person 
ceasing to be a member shall, unless disqualified under section 4, be 
eligible for re- appointment as such.


</article>



<article><tid>86934</tid>
<number> 8</number> Meetings.
<section><tid>1018312</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall meet at such times and  
places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at  
  meetings) as may be provided by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1272684</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman, or, if for any reason he is unable to attend 
any meeting, any other member chosen by the members present at the 
meeting, shall preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>442456</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the 
Authority shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the members 
present and voting, and, in the event of an equality of votes, the 
Chair-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>63</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

man, or in his absence, the person presiding, shall have and exercise 
a second or casting vote.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1651614</tid>
<number>9</number>Vacancy in the Authority not to invalidate proceedings. No act 
or proceeding of the Authority shall be deemed to be invalid by reason 
merely of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the 
Authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1772024</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appointment of officers and other employees of the Authority.

<section><tid>1621219</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of enabling it efficiently to discharge its  
functions under this Act, the Authority shall, subject to the 
provisions of section 12 and to such rules as may be prescribed in 
this behalf, appoint (whether on deputation or otherwise) such number 
of officers and other employees as it may consider necessary:
Provided that the appointment of such category of officers as may 
be specified after consultation with the Chairman in such rules, shall 
be subject to the approval of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>673673</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of section 12, every officer or 
other employee appointed by the Authority shall be subject to such 
conditions of service and shall be entitled to such remuneration as 
may be determined by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>603849</tid>
<number>11</number>Authority to act on business principles. In the discharge of 
its functions under this Act, the Authority shall act, so far as may 
be, on business principles.
CHAP

PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS

CHAPTER III

PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS



</article>



<article><tid>1797730</tid>
<number> 12</number> Transfer assets and liabilities of Central Government to the 
Authority.
<section><tid>1956048</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (2), as from  
such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may appoint by notification in 
the Official Gazette in relation to any airport,--

<subsection><tid>1157532</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties and other assets vested in the Central 
Government for the purposes of the airport and 
administered by the Director- General of Civil Aviation 
immediately before such day shall vest in the 
Authority:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1556663</tid>
<number>b</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all 
contracts entered into and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with, or for the Central 
Government immediately before such day for or in 
connection with the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>64</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 4- <year>1972</year>: vide Notification No. S. O. 168 (E), dated 24- 2- <year>1972</year>, 
Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Section 3 (ii), P. 389, in 
relation to the aerodromes of Bombay (Santa Cruz), Calcutta (Dum Dum), 
Delhi (Palam) and Madras (Meenambakkam).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


purposes of the airport shall be deemed to have been 
incurred, entered into and engaged to be done by, with, 
or for the Authority;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1748838</tid>
<number>c</number>all non- recurring expenditure incurred by the Central 
Government for or in connection with the purposes of 
the airport up to such day and declared to be capital 
expenditure by the Central Government shall, subject to 
such terms and conditions as may be determined by the 
Central Government, be treated as the capital provided 
by the Central Government to the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1749823</tid>
<number>d</number>all sums of money due to the Central Government in 
relation to the airport immediately before such day 
shall be deemed to be due to the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1963710</tid>
<number>e</number>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or 
which could have been instituted by or against the 
Central Government immediately before such day for any 
matter in relation to the airport may be continued or 
instituted by or against the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>160275</tid>
<number>f</number>every employee holding any office under the Central 
Government immediately before such day solely or mainly 
for or in connection with such affairs of the airport 
as are relevant to the functions of the Authority under 
this Act shall be treated as on deputation with the 
Authority but shall hold his office in the Authority by 
the same tenure and upon the same terms and conditions 
of service as respects remuneration, leave, provident 
fund, retirement or other terminal benefits as he would 
have held such office, if the Authority had not been 
constituted and shall continue to do so until the 
Central Government, either on its own motion or at the 
request of the Authority, recalls such employee to its 
service or until the Authority, with the concurrence of 
the Central Government, duly absorbs such employee in 
its regular service, whichever is earlier:
Provided that during the period of deputation of any such 
employee with the Authority, the Authority shall pay to 
the Central Government, in respect of every such 
employee, such contribution towards his leave salary, 
pension and gratuity as the Central Government may, by 
order, determine:

Provided further that any such employee, who has, in respect 
of the proposal of the Authority to absorb him in its


<pagefootnote><pagenum>65</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

regular service, intimated within such time as may be 
specified in this behalf by the Authority his intention 
of not becoming a regular employee of the Authority, 
shall not be absorbed by the Authority in its regular 
service.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1030974</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the date determined by the Central Government under 
the proviso to sub- section (2) of section 16,--

<subsection><tid>1073976</tid>
<number>a</number>the equipment and appliances relating to air navigation 
services and the buildings used exclusively for such 
services immediately before such day shall vest in the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1675899</tid>
<number>b</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all 
contracts entered into and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with, or for the Central 
Government immediately before such day for or in 
connection with air navigation services shall be deemed 
to have been incurred, entered into and engaged to be 
done by, with, or for the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1938559</tid>
<number>c</number>all sums of money due to the Central Government for or 
in connection with air navigation services immediately 
before such day shall be deemed to be due to the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>252854</tid>
<number>d</number>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or 
which could have been instituted by or against the 
Central Government immediately before such day for any 
matter in connection with air navigation services may 
be continued or instituted by or against the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259340</tid>
<number>e</number>every employee holding any office under the Central 
Government immediately before such day solely or mainly 
for or in connection with air navigation services shall 
be treated as on deputation with the Authority but 
shall hold his office in the Authority by the same 
tenure and upon the same terms and conditions of 
service as respects remuneration, leave, provident 
fund, retirement or other terminal benefits as he would 
have held such office if the Authority had not been 
constituted and shall continue to do so until the 
Central Government, either on its own motion or at the 
request of the Authority, recalls such employee to its 
service or until the Authority, with the concurrence of 
the Central Government, duly absorbs such employee in 
its regular service, whichever is earlier:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>66</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that during the period of deputation of any such 
employee with the Authority, the Authority shall pay to 
the Central Government, in respect of every such 
employee, such contribution towards his leave salary, 
pension and gratuity as the Central Government may, by 
order, determine:

Provided further that any such employee, who has, in respect 
of the proposal of the Authority to absorb him in its 
regular service, intimated within such time as may be 
specified in this behalf by the Authority his intention 
of not becoming a regular employee of the Authority, 
shall not be absorbed by the Authority in its regular 
service.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>493460</tid>
<number>3</number>If any dispute or doubt arises as to which of the properties, 
rights or liabilities of the Central Government have been transferred 
to the Authority or as to which of the employees serving under the 
Central Government are to be treated as on deputation with the 
Authority, under this section, such dispute or doubt shall be decided 
by the Central Government in consultation with the Authority and the 
decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1429137</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>.) or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the absorption of any employee by the Authority in its regular 
service under this section shall not entitle such employee to any 
compensation under that Act or other law and no such claim shall be 
entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>643825</tid>
<number>5</number>In this section and in section 16, the expression" air 
navigation services", in relation to any airport, means air traffic 
services (including aeronautical and flight information services), 
aeronautical communication and navigational aids and meteorological 
services at such airport.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>809019</tid>
<number>13</number>Compulsory acquisition of land for the Authority. Any land 
required by the Authority for discharging its functions under this Act 
shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land may be 
acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the Land 
Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>.) or of any other corresponding law 
for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1159009</tid>
<number>14</number>Contracts by the Authority. Subject to the provisions of 
section 15, the Authority shall be competent to enter into and perform 
any contract necessary for the discharge of its functions under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>67</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1306159</tid>
<number> 15</number> Mode of executing contracts on behalf of the Authority.
<section><tid>1381062</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every contract shall, on behalf of the Authority, be made by the 
Chairman or such other member or such officer of the Authority as may 
be generally or specially empowered in this behalf by the Authority 
and such contracts or class of contracts as may be specified in the 
regulations shall be sealed with the common seal of the Authority:
Provided that no contract exceeding such value or amount as the 
Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix in this 
behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by the 
Authority:

Provided further that no contract for the acquisition or sale of 
immovable property or for the lease of any such property for a term 
exceeding thirty years and no other contract exceeding such value or 
amount as the Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix 
in this behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by 
the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1346220</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the form and 
manner in which any contract shall be made under this Act shall be 
such as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>680968</tid>
<number>3</number>No contract which is not in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act and the regulations shall be binding on the Authority.
CHAP

FUNCTIONS OF THE AUTHORITY

CHAPTER IV

FUNCTIONS OF THE AUTHORITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1949888</tid>
<number> 16</number> Functions of the Authority.
<section><tid>75222</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the rules, if any,  
made by the Central Government in this behalf, it shall be the 
function of the Authority to manage the airports efficiently.

</section>

<section><tid>546528</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Authority to provide at the 
airports such services and facilities as are necessary or desirable 
for the efficient operation of air transport services thereat:
Provided that the function of providing air navigation services 
at the airports shall continue to be discharged by the Central 
Government until such date as that Government may, by order, 
determine.


</section>

<section><tid>1771504</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in sub- section (1) and (2) the Authority may--

<subsection><tid>509303</tid>
<number>a</number>plan, develop, construct and maintain runways, taxiways, 
aprons and terminal and ancillary buildings at the 
airports;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>68</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>910215</tid>
<number>b</number>construct residential buildings and create townships for 
its employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765418</tid>
<number>c</number>establish and maintain hotels, restaurants and rest- 
rooms at or near the airports;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1113097</tid>
<number>d</number>establish warehouses at the airports for the storage or 
processing of goods;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1701612</tid>
<number>e</number>arrange for postal, money exchange, insurance and 
telephone facilities for the use of passengers and 
other persons at the airports;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>861840</tid>
<number>f</number>make appropriate arrangements for watch and ward at the 
airports;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>899126</tid>
<number>g</number>regulate and control the plying of vehicles, and the 
entry and exit of passengers and visitors, in the 
airports with due regard to the protocol functions of 
the Government of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>609194</tid>
<number>h</number>develop and provide consultancy services in India and 
abroad in relation to planning and development of 
airports or any facilities thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1373397</tid>
<number>i</number>establish and manage heliports and airstrips;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901081</tid>
<number>j</number>provide such transport facilities as are, in the opinion 
of the Authority, necessary to the passengers 
travelling by air;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>94789</tid>
<number>k</number>form one or more companies under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (1 of <year>1956</year>.) or under any other law relating to 
companies to further the efficient discharge of the 
functions imposed on it by this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>860074</tid>
<number>l</number>take all such steps as may be necessary or convenient 
for, or may be incidental to, the exercise of any power 
or the discharge of any function conferred or imposed 
on it by this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1584716</tid>
<number>4</number>In the discharge of its functions under this section, the 
Authority shall have due regard to the development of air transport 
service and to the efficiency, economy and safety of such service.

</section>

<section><tid>1885284</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed as--

<subsection><tid>371670</tid>
<number>a</number>imposing an obligation on the Authority to discharge any 
function or duty under this section with respect to any 
airport in relation to which a notification has not 
been issued under sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1005204</tid>
<number>b</number>authorising the disregard by the Authority of any law 
for the time being in force; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>69</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>577820</tid>
<number>c</number>authorising any person to institute any proceeding 
in respect of a duty or liability to which the 
Authority or its officers or other employees would 
not otherwise be subject.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER V

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389168</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power of the Authority to charge fees, rent, etc. The 
Authority may,--
<section><tid>293755</tid>
<number>i</number>with the previous approval of the Central Government, 
charge fees or rent,--

<subsection><tid>1139220</tid>
<number>a</number>for the landing, housing or parking of 
aircrafts or for any other service or facility 
offered in connection with aircraft operations, at 
any airport, heliport or airstrip.
Explanation.-- In this sub- clause" aircraft" 
does not include an aircraft belonging to the 
Indian Defence Services and" aircraft operations" 
do not include operations of any aircraft 
belonging to the said Services;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>11987</tid>
<number>b</number>for the amenities given to the passengers 
and visitors at any airport, heliport or airstrip;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1511270</tid>
<number>c</number>for the use and enjoyment by persons of 
facilities and other services provided by the 
Authority at any airport, heliport or airstrip;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>994904</tid>
<number>ii</number>with due regard to the instructions that the Central 
Government may give to the Authority, from time to 
time, charge fees or rent from persons who are given by 
the Authority any facility for carrying on any trade or 
business at any airport.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>344247</tid>
<number> 18</number> Additional capital and grants to tee Authority bu the Central 
Government. The Central Government may, after due appropriation made 
by Parliament by law in this behalf,--
<section><tid>34745</tid>
<number>a</number>provide any capital, over and above the capital provided 
under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 12, that 
may be required by the Authority for the discharge of 
its functions under this Act or for any purpose 
connected therewith on such terms and conditions as 
that Government may determine;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>70</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>580729</tid>
<number>b</number>pay to the Authority, on such terms and conditions as 
the Central Government may determine, by way of loans 
or grants such sums of money as that Government may 
consider necessary for the efficient discharge by the 
Authority of its functions under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>819574</tid>
<number> 19</number> Fund of the Authority.
<section><tid>1324045</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall have its own  
fund and all receipts of the Authority shall be credited thereto and 
all payments of the Authority shall be made therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>394912</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall have power, subject to the provisions of 
this Act, to spend such sums as it thinks fit to cover all 
administrative expenses of the Authority and on objects or for 
purposes authorised by this Act and such sums shall be treated as 
expenditure out of the fund of the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>537924</tid>
<number>3</number>All moneys standing at the credit of the Authority which 
cannot immediately be applied as provided in sub- section (2) shall be 
deposited in the State Bank of India or in such scheduled bank or 
banks and subject to such conditions as may from time to time be 
specified by the Central Government.
Explanation.-- In this sub- section" scheduled bank" has the same 
meaning as in clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India 
Act, <year>1934</year>. (2 of <year>1934</year>.)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1329654</tid>
<number> 20</number> Allocation of surplus funds.
<section><tid>116791</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may, from time  
to time, set apart such amounts as it thinks fit as a reserve fund or 
funds for the purpose of expanding existing facilities or services or 
creating new facilities or services at any airport or for the purpose 
of providing against any temporary decrease of revenue or increase of 
expenditure from transient causes or for purposes of replacement or 
for meeting expenditure arising from loss or damage from fire, 
cyclone, air- crash or other accident or for meeting any liability 
arising out of any act or omission in the discharge of its functions 
under this Act:
Provided that without prejudice to the right of the Authority to 
establish specific reserves for one or more specific purposes, the 
Authority shall also have the power to establish a general reserve:

Provided further that the sums set apart annually in respect of 
each or any of the specific and general reserves and the aggregate at 
any time of such sums shall not exceed such limits as may, from time 
to time, be fixed in that behalf by the Central Government.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>441139</tid>
<number>2</number>After making provision for such reserve fund or funds and for 
bad and doubtful debts, depreciation in assets and all other matters 
which are usually provided for by companies registered and 
incorporated under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) the Authority 
shall pay the balance of its annual net profits to the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1807275</tid>
<number> 21</number> Submission of programme of activities and financial 
estimates.
<section><tid>1294841</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall, before the commencement of each  
financial year, prepare a statement of the programme of its activities 
during the forthcoming financial year as well as a financial estimate 
in respect thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1840016</tid>
<number>2</number>The statement prepared under sub- section (1) shall, not less 
than three months before the commencement of each financial year be 
submitted for approval to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1004006</tid>
<number>3</number>The statement and the financial estimates of the Authority, 
may, with the approval of the Central Government, be revised by the 
Authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>669537</tid>
<number>22</number>Investment of funds. The Authority may invest its funds 
 (including any reserve fund) in the securities of the Central 
Government or in such other manner as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>200737</tid>
<number> 23</number> Borrowing powers of the Authority.
<section><tid>214958</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority may,  
with the consent of the Central Government or in accordance with the 
terms of any general or special authority given to it by the Central 
Government, borrow money from any source by the issue of bonds, 
debentures or such other instruments as it may deem fit for 
discharging all or any of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1184871</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may guarantee in such manner as it 
thinks fit the repayment of the principal and the payment of interest 
thereon with respect to the loans borrowed by the Authority under sub- 
section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1138790</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to such limits as the Central Government may, from 
time to time, lay down, the Authority may borrow temporarily by way of 
overdraft or otherwise such amounts as it may require for discharging 
its functions under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1401277</tid>
<number> 24</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>607712</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts including the profit and loss account and the balance- sheet 
in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1102183</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Authority shall be audited annually by 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure 
incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Authority to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>915332</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Authority shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has 
in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of book, 
accounts, connected vouchers, documents and papers and inspect any, of 
the offices of the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>625996</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in 
this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded 
annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the 
same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>141898</tid>
<number> 25</number> Submission of annual reports to Parliament.
<section><tid>1635752</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority  
shall, as soon as may be after the end of each financial year, prepare 
and submit to the Central Government in such form as may be prescribed 
a report giving an account of its activities during that financial 
year and the report shall also give an account of the activities which 
are likely to be undertaken by the Authority during the next financial 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>56256</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall cause such report to be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after it is 
submitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1433020</tid>
<number>26</number>Delegation. The Authority may, by general or special order in 
writing delegate to the Chairman or any other member or to any officer 
of the Authority, subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, 
as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions 
under this Act (except the powers under section 37) as it may, deem 
necessary.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>961639</tid>
<number>27</number>Authentication of orders and other Instruments of the 
Authority. All orders and decisions of the Authority shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the Chairman or any other member 
authorised by the Authority in this behalf and all other instruments 
executed by the Authority shall be authenticated by the signature of 
an officer of the Authority authorised by the Authority in this 
behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>916788</tid>
<number>28</number>Officers and employees of the Authority to be public 
servants. All officers and employees of the Authority shall, when 
acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act 
or of any rule or regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (5  
  of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1060195</tid>
<number>29</number>Protection of action taken under the Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Authority 
or any member or any officer or other employee of the Authority for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or of any rule or regulation made thereunder or 
for any damage sustained by any aircraft or vehicle in consequence of 
any defect in any of the airports or other things belonging to or 
under the control of the Authority.


</article>



<article><tid>308544</tid>
<number>30</number>Custody and disposal of lost Property. Subject to such 
regulations as the Authority may make in this behalf, the Authority 
shall provide for securing the safe custody and restoration of any 
property which, while not in proper custody, is found on any permises 
belonging to the Authority or under its overall control or in any 
aircraft on any such premises.


</article>



<article><tid>371233</tid>
<number>31</number>Provisions relating to income- tax. For the purposes of the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>.) or any other enactment for the time 
being in force relating to income- tax or any other tax on income, 
profits or gains, the Authority shall be deemed to be a company within 
the meaning of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> and shall be liable to tax 
accordingly on its income, profits and gains.


</article>



<article><tid>1368144</tid>
<number>32</number>Power of the Authority to undertake certain works. The 
Authority may undertake to carry out on behalf of any person any works 
or services or any class of works or services on such terms and 
conditions as may be agreed upon between the Authority and the person 
concerned.


</article>



<article><tid>1179633</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power of Central Government to temporarily divest the 
Authority of the managements of the airport.
<section><tid>1208511</tid>
<number>1</number>If at any time the  
Central Government is of opinion that in the public interest it is 
necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by order, direct the 
Authority to entrust the management of any airport with effect from 
such date and to such person as may be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>74</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authority of the management of the airport specified in the order and 
the Authority shall be bound to comply with such direction:

Provided that before an order is made under this sub- section the 
Authority shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in 
the matter.


</section>

<section><tid>1259690</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the management of any airport is entrusted to any 
person specified under sub- section (1)  (hereafter in this section  
  referred to as the authorised person), the Authority shall cease to 
exercise and discharge all its powers and functions under this Act in 
relation to such airport and such powers and functions shall be 
exercised and discharged by the authorised person in accordance with 
the instructions, if any, which the Central Government may give to the 
authorised person from time to time:
Provided that no such power or function as may be specified by 
the Central Government by a general or special order shall be 
exercised or discharged by the authorised person except with the 
previous sanction of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1731876</tid>
<number>3</number>An order made under sub- section (1) shall, unless rescinded, 
be in operation for a period of six months from the date on which the 
management of the airport is entrusted to the authorised person:
Provided that the Central Government may extend such period for a 
further period or periods not exceeding eighteen months.


</section>

<section><tid>1839151</tid>
<number>4</number>During the operation of an order made under sub- section (1), 
it shall be competent for the Central Government to issue, from time 
to time, such directions to the Authority as are necessary to enable 
the authorised person to exercise the powers and discharge the 
functions of the Authority under this Act in relation to the airport, 
the management of which has been entrusted to him and in particular to 
transfer any sum of money from the fund of the Authority to the 
authorised person for the management of the airport and every such 
direction shall be complied with by the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>209785</tid>
<number>5</number>On the cesser of operation of any order made under sub- 
section (1) in relation to any airport, the authorised person shall 
cease to exercise and perform the powers and functions of the 
Authority under this Act in relation to such airport and the Authority 
shall continue to exercise and perform such powers and functions in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1984217</tid>
<number>6</number>On the cesser of operation of any order made under sub- 
section (1) in relation to any airport, the authorised person shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>75</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

hand over to the Authority any property (including any sum of money or  
  other asset) remaining with him in connection with the management of 
such airport.


</section>

<section><tid>6243</tid>
<number>7</number>Anything done or any action taken lawfully by the authorised 
person in relation to any airport during the period of operation of an 
order made under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken by the Authority and shall be binding on the Authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693327</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power of Central Government to supersed the Authority.
<section><tid>946446</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion--

<subsection><tid>1113688</tid>
<number>a</number>that on account of a grave emergency, the Authority is 
unable to discharge the functions and duties imposed on 
it by or under the provisions of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1254374</tid>
<number>b</number>that the Authority has persistently made default in 
complying with any direction issued by the Central 
Government under this Act or in the discharge of the 
functions and duties imposed on it by or under the 
provisions of this Act and as a result of which default 
the financial position of the Authority or the 
administration of any airport has deteriorated; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>386133</tid>
<number>c</number>that circumstances exist which render it necessary in 
the public interest so to do,
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
supersede the Authority for such period, not exceeding six months, as 
may be specified in the notification:

Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub- 
section for the reasons mentioned in clause (b), the Central 
Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Authority to 
show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the 
explanations and objections, if any, of the Authority.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1860210</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the publication of a notification under sub- section (1) 
superseding the Authority,--

<subsection><tid>918189</tid>
<number>a</number>all the members shall, as from the date of supersession, 
vacate their offices as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>17556</tid>
<number>b</number>all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or 
under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or 
discharged by or on behalf of the Authority shall, 
until the Authority is re- constituted under sub- section 
 (3), be exercised and discharged by such person or 
persons as the Central Government may direct;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>76</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290724</tid>
<number>c</number>all property owned or controlled by the Authority shall, 
until the Authority is re- constituted under sub- section 
 (3), vest in the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1036047</tid>
<number>3</number>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in 
the notification issued under sub- section (1) the Central Government 
may--

<subsection><tid>228455</tid>
<number>a</number>extend the period of supersession for such further term, 
not exceeding six months, as it may consider necessary; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>420699</tid>
<number>b</number>re- constitute the Authority by fresh appointment and in 
such case any persons who vacated their offices under 
clause (a) of sub- section (2) shall not be deemed 
disqualified for appointment:
Provided that the Central Government may, at any time before the 
expiration of the period of supersession, whether as originally 
specified under sub- section (1) or as extended under sub- section, take 
action under clause (b) of this sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1247675</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause a notification issued 
under sub- section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this 
section and the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before 
both Houses of Parliament at the earliest opportunity.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1541128</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power of Central Government to issue directions.
<section><tid>967355</tid>
<number>1</number>Without  
prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority 
shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be 
bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
Government may give in writing to it from time to time:
Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be 
given opportunity to express its views before any direction is given 
under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>1677089</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is 
one of policy or not shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1791768</tid>
<number> 36</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>779537</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the purposes of the Act.

</section>

<section><tid>736670</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>80460</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions of service of the Chairman and other 
members under section 5 including the salaries payable 
to the Chairman and to the members who are required to 
render whole- time service and the fees and allowances 
payable to the members who are required to render part- 
time service;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>77</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>433413</tid>
<number>b</number>the period of notice required to terminate the 
appointment of any member, who is required to render 
part- time service and who is not a servant of the 
Government, under section 5, and the period of notice 
that may be given to the Central Government by a member 
before he resigns his office, under that section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1012354</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions and limitations subject to which the 
Authority may appoint officers and other employees 
under sub- section (1) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>775911</tid>
<number>d</number>the terms and conditions subject to which the non- 
recurring expenditure incurred by the Central 
Government for or in connection with the purposes of 
any airport shall be treated as the capital provided by 
the Central Government to the Authority under clause 
 (c) of sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1727256</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which the Authority may invest its funds 
under section 22;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108853</tid>
<number>f</number>the form in which the Authority shall prepare the annual 
statement of accounts including the profit and loss 
account and the balance- sheet under section 24; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>569308</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>340642</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The power to make rules conferred by clauses (a) and (c) 
of sub- section (2) shall include the power to give retrospective 
effect, from a date not earlier than the date of commencement of this 
Act, to such rules or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be 
given to any rule so as to prejudicially affect the interests of any 
person to whom such rule may be applicable.]

</section>

<section><tid>494113</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>906768</tid>
<number> 37</number> Power of the Authority to make regulations.
<section><tid>192938</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority  
may make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary 
or expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1221220</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such regulations may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1021312</tid>
<number>a</number>the times and places of the meetings of the Authority 
and the procedure to be followed for the transaction of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 72 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (Retrospectively). 
2 Subs. by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


business at such meetings under sub- section (1) of 
section 8;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>941290</tid>
<number>b</number>the conditions of service and the remuneration of 
officers and other employees appointed by the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>951425</tid>
<number>c</number>the contracts or class of contracts which are to be 
sealed with the common seal of the Authority and the 
form and manner in which a contract may be made by the 
Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001942</tid>
<number>d</number>the storage or processing of goods in any warehouse 
established by the Authority under clause (d) of sub- 
section (3) of section 16 and the charging of fees for 
such storage or processing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>671548</tid>
<number>e</number>the custody and restoration of lost property and the 
terms and conditions under which lost property may be 
restored to the person entitled thereto, under section 
30;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607469</tid>
<number>f</number>the disposal of any lost property in cases where such 
property is not restored under section 30;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>215391</tid>
<number>g</number>securing the safety of aircraft, vehicles, and persons 
using the airport and preventing danger to the public 
arising from the use and operation of aircraft in the 
airport;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>770419</tid>
<number>h</number>preventing obstruction within the airport for its normal 
functioning;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1148051</tid>
<number>i</number>prohibiting the parking or waiting of any vehicle or 
carriage within the airport except at places specified 
by the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>309755</tid>
<number>j</number>prohibiting or restricting access to any part of the 
airport;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1221598</tid>
<number>k</number>preserving order within the airport and preventing 
damage to property therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1930368</tid>
<number>l</number>regulating or restricting advertising within the 
airport;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>430308</tid>
<number>m</number>requiring any person, if so directed by an officer 
appointed by the Authority in this behalf, to leave the 
airport or any particular part of the airport; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064874</tid>
<number>n</number>generally for the efficient and proper management of the 
airport.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>362517</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The power to make regulations conferred by clause (b) of 
sub- section (2) shall include the power to give retrospective effect, 
from a date not earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, to 
such regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be 
given to any regulation so as to prejudicially affect the interests of 
any person to whom such regulation may be applicable.]

</section>

<section><tid>1383137</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause every regulation made 
under this section to be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
regulation, or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be 
made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1579822</tid>
<number> 38</number> Supplemental provisions respecting regulations.
<section><tid>449881</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
regulation which may be made by the Authority under this Act may be 
made by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette 
within one year of the constitution of the Authority and any 
regulation so made may be altered or rescinded by the Authority by 
means of a regulation made by it under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 72 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>78259</tid>
<number>2</number>No regulation made by the Authority under this Act shall have 
effect until it has been approved by the Central Government and 
published in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1878335</tid>
<number>39</number>Penalty for breach of certain regulations. Any regulation 
made under any of the clauses (g) to (m)  (inclusive) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 37 may provide that a contravention thereof shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in 
the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine which 
may extend to twenty rupees for every day during which such 
contravention continues after conviction for the first such 
contravention.


</article>



<article><tid>1889024</tid>
<number> 40</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>228387</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, 
make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act 
as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the 
difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiration of 
one year from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>561728</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two successive sessions and if before the expiry 
of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
following both Houses agree in making any modification in the order or 
both Houses agree that the order should not be made, the order shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1878239</tid>
<number>41</number>[ Amendment of Act 22 of <year>1934</year>.] Not reproduced.

</article>



 </act>