<act> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—These 
Rules may be called the Central Reserve Police Force Rules, 1955.
  


</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “The Act” means the Central 
Reserve Police Force Act, 1949 (Act No. LXVI of 1949);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “Commandant” means the 
Commandant appointed to the Force;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “Deputy Inspector General of 
Police” means an officer who has been notified by the Central Government as 
Deputy Inspector General of Police for the Force;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “Detachment” includes any part 
of the Force required or ordered to proceed on duty away from headquarters;
 

     1[(dd)  “Director General” means 
the Director General of the Force appointed by the Central Government through 
whom the superintendence of, and control over, the Force of the Central 
Government shall be exercised and who shall, subject to any instructions that 
the Central Government may give, administer the Force in accordance with the 
provisions of the Act and of these or other rules;]
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “The Force” means the Central 
Reserve Police Force;
 

     2[(ee)  “Additional Director 
General” means an officer who has been appointed by the Central Government as 
Additional Director General of Police for the Force and who shall subject to 
supervision, control and directions of the Director General, perform such 
functions and exercise such financial and other powers as may be authorised by 
the Director General by general or special order and exercise such financial 
powers as may be delegated to him by the Central Government;]
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  “Inspector General” means an 
officer who has been notified by the Central Government as Inspector General of 
Police for the Force and who will 

3[subject to the supervision, 
control, and direction of the Director General] exercise the powers of the Head 
of the Department;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act;
 

        4[(h)  “Subordinate Officer” 
means a member of the Force of the rank of Subedar Major, Subedar, 
Sub-Inspector;]
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  “Superior Officer” means an 
officer appointed to the Force by the Central Government under sub-section (1) 
of section 4 and includes a person officiating for any such officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  “Under Officer” means a member 
of the Force of the rank of Head Constable, Naik or Lance Naik.
 
 







</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Interpretation.—In 
these Rules unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  The expressions “Battalion” and 
“Company” have the meanings assigned to them as in the Army.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “Local Promotee” means a 

1[Subordinate Officer] who has been 
enlisted in the Force and promoted to the rank of Deputy Superintendent of 
Police (Company Commander, Quarter Master or Wireless).
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The expression “other directly 
recruited” relates to officers appointed directly to the gazetted ranks in the 
Force from outside the Force.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Powers of the Central 
Government and Certain Officers of the Force.—1[
<section><number>a</number> 
In all cases not specifically provided for in these rules, instructions issued 
from time to time by the Central Government or the Director General or under 
his directions by the Additional Director General or the Inspector General 
shall regulate working of the Force.]
 

2[***]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>

1[<number>4A</number> Composition 
of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Central Reserve Police Force shall be constituted as follows:
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Central Reserve Police Force 
(Regular);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Central Reserve Police Force 
(Auxiliary);
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Officers, Subordinate 
Officers and other persons appointed to or enrolled into the Central Reserve 
Police Force (Regular) shall be liable for continuous service for the term 
mentioned in their enrolment form, letter of appointment or in the rules made 
in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Officers, Subordinate 
Officers and other persons appointed to or enrolled into the Central Reserve 
Police Force (Auxiliary) shall serve as and when they are called out for 
service by the Director General with the consent of the Central Government or 
for training under the order of the Director General.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE  
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Members of the Force.—All the officers and men mentioned in rule 5 shall 
be deemed to be the members of the Force.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appointments other 
than that of Superior Officers.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Officers and men mentioned in rule 5(b) and 5(c) shall be appointed—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  by direct recruitment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  by deputation from Army or State 
Police Forces;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  by promotion as laid down in 
Chapter IX.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The authority to make 
appointments to the various non-gazetted ranks shall be the Commandant, 
provided that, in the case of Sub-Inspectors and Subedar (Inspectors) prior 
approval of the Deputy Inspector General of Police and of the Inspector General 
respectively shall be obtained.
 

1[(c) Non-Gazetted 
Officers and men of all ranks shall be enrolled subject to sub-rule (b) above 
by the Commandant in the manner prescribed in section 5 and be appointed by him 
as member of the Force.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Seniority.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The seniority of Superior Officers shall be in the following order:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Commandant or Principal, 
Central Training College.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Assistant Commandant(Second-in-Command) 
or Adjutant or Junior Staff Officer or Vice-Principal, Central Training 
College.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  Company Commander or Quarter 
Master or Assistant Principal, Central Training College.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The inter se 
seniority of Superior Officers shall be determined as under:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  An Army Officer shall maintain 
his seniority as between Army Officers, within a particular rank. Similarly, an 
Indian Police Service Officer shall maintain his seniority between himself and 
other Indian Police Service officers.
 
                 For purposes of inter se 
seniority between non-Army and Army Officers of eqivalent rank, substantive 
incumbents shall be senior to officiating or temporary officers, their inter 
se seniority depending on the dates of their continued unbroken service in 
that rank. Similarly, the inter se seniority officiating or temporary 
officers shall be determined by their continuous length of service in that 
rank. An Army Officer re-employed in the Central Reserve Police Force shall 
maintain his Army seniority between Army officers within a particular rank.
 

        1[(ii)  The inter-se 
seniority of direct recruits to the Central Reserve Police Force in the rank of 
Company Commander or Quarter Master or Assistant Principal, Central Training 
College, shall be determined in accordance with the aggregate marks obtained by 
them before the selection board and at the passing out examinations conducted 
after their basic training at the Central Reserve Police Force, Internal 
Security Academy.
 
An officer promoted 
locally in the Central Reserve Police Force or from a Subordinate Police 
Service in the State shall take rank immediately below the entire batch of 
direct recruits, any officer of which may have been appointed on the same date, 
the inter-se seniority between local promotees from the States shall be 
determined with reference to their dates of birth.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> The seniority of 
person promoted to the rank of subordinate or under officer shall be determined 
in the following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  before confirmation every such 
officer shall take his seniority from the date of his continuously holding such 
rank; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  on confirmation, he shall take 
his seniority from the date of such confirmation:
 
Provided that in the case 
of officers confirmed on the same date they will take their seniority from the 
date of their promotion in the rank:
 
Provided further that in 
the case of officers where the date of confirmation and the date of promotion 
are the same their seniority immediately before such promotion shall remain 
unaffected.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number> For those directly 
recruited as subordinate or under officer, their seniority shall be determined 
in the following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  before confirmation every such 
officer shall take his seniority in the rank to which he is so recruited in 
accordance with the order of merit at the recruitment test; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  on confirmation, he shall take 
his seniority from the date of such confirmation:
 
Provided that in the case 
of officers confirmed on the same date, they will take their seniority in 
accordance with the order of merit at the recruitment test.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number> A person promoted to 
a higher rank and a person recruited direct to the same rank shall have their 
seniority from the date of appointment to that rank subject to the condition 
that if both were appointed on the same date, the former (promotee) shall be 
senior:
 
Provided further that if 
the date of confirmation is the same their seniority immediately before such 
confirmation shall remain unaffected.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> Those recruited as 
constables shall take their seniority from the date of their first appointment:
 
Provided that on 
confirmation they will take their seniority in accordance with the date of 
their confirmation:
 
Provided further that if 
the date of confirmation is same a person of higher age will be senior in rank 
to a person of lower age.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Attestation of oath or 
affirmation.—1[
<section><number>a</number> 
The oath or affirmation set out in Appendix ‘C’ to these rules shall be 
administered with due ceremony by the Commandant (or any superior officer 
appointed by him in this behalf) to all officers and rank and file. The officer 
administering the oath or an affirmation shall attest that he has done so by 
signing an attestation paper which shall be attached to the Character and 
Service Roll of the member of the Force concerned.]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Attestation may be 
waived by the Commandant in the case of those officers and men on deputation 
who have already taken such an oath or affirmation elsewhere.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Recruitment.—
<section><number>a</number> 
A candidate for enlistment in the Force must conform to the standard laid down 
in rule 11 below, must bear a good character and must be 
<subsection><number>a</number> citizen of India, 
or (b) a person who has migrated from Pakistan with the intention of 
permanently settling in India, or (c) a subject of Nepal or of a Portuguese 
possession in India, and if he comes under category (b) or (c) must be a person 
in whose favour a certificate of eligibility has been given by the Government 
of India. A candidate in whose case a certificate is necessary may, however, be 
appointed provisionally subject to the necessary certificate being eventually 
given to him by Government:
 
Provided ex-convicts, or 
Army or Police deserters shall not be enlisted.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> No man who has more 
than one wife living shall be eligible for enlistment in the Force, provided 
that the Central Government may if satisfied that there are special grounds for 
doing so, exempt any person from the operation of this condition.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Health Certificate.—No 
candidate shall be enrolled unless he obtains a health certificate in the 
prescribed Form CRP-I signed by Medical Superintendent and Staff Surgeon, 
Central Reserve Police Hospital, Neemuch, or by a Civil Surgeon or by a 
Recruiting Medical Officer.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Recruiting Roll.—Every 
member of the Force shall sign, or if illiterate place his thumb impression 
mark on the agreement in Form CRP-I. This form on completion shall be attached 
to the Character and Service Roll of the member of the Force concerned.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Verification.—
<section><number>a</number> 
As soon as a man is enrolled, his character, antecedents, connections and age 
shall be verified in accordance with the procedure prescribed by the Central 
Government from time to time. The Verification Roll shall be sent to the 
District Magistrate or Deputy Commissioner of the District of which the recruit 
is a resident.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Verification Roll 
shall be in CRP Form-25 and after verification shall be attached to the 
Character and Service Roll of the member of the Force concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The Commandant may 
waive verification in the case of men who have been enrolled in the Force 
within six months of their discharge from the regular Army.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Plural marriages.—No 
member of the Force who has wife living shall contract any other marriage 
without first obtaining the permission of the Government notwithstanding that 
such subsequent marriage is permissible under the personal law for the time 
being applicable to the member of the Force.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Period of Service.—
<section><number>a</number> 
All members of the Force shall be enrolled for a period of three years. During 
this period of engagement, they shall be liable to discharge at any time on one 
month’s notice by the appointing authority. At the end of this period those not 
given substantive status shall be considered for quasi-permanency under the 
provision of the Central Civil Services (Temporary Service) Rules, 1965. Those 
not declared quasi-permanent under the said rules shall be continued as 
temporary Government employees unless they claim discharge as per schedule to 
the Act. Those who are temporary shall be liable to discharge on one month’s 
notice and those who are quasi-permanent shall be liable to discharge on three 
months’ notice in accordance with the said rules, as amended from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Should the Central 
Government decide at any time to disband the Force or any part of it either 
before termination of the period for which a member of the Force is enrolled or 
at any time thereafter, he shall be liable to discharge, without compensation 
from the date of disbandment.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> No member of the 
Force shall withdraw from the duties of his office without the express 
permission of the Commandant or an accredited gazetted officer.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The appointing 
authority may, during the period of initial appointment of a member of the 
Force appointed under 

1[section 4 and 5] 
of the Act, permit him, for good and sufficient reason, to resign from the 
Force with effect from such date as may be specified in the order accepting his 
resignation:
 
Provided that on the 
acceptance of his resignation any such member of the Force shall be required to 
refund to the Government all the cost of training imparted to him in the Force 
or a sum equal to three months’ pay and allowances, received by him prior to 
the date of his resignation whichever is less.
 
Explanation.—(1) 
For the purpose of this sub-clause “during the period of initial appointment” 
shall mean the period before a member of the Force is declared quasi-permanent.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> The appointing 
authority may refuse to permit a member of the Force to resign if any emergency 
has been declared in the country either due to internal disturbances or 
external aggression.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number> The appointing 
authority may give substantive status to such members of the Force as are found 
suitable in all respect.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Discharge.—Subject 
to the provisions of the Schedule appended to the Act, any member of the Force 
shall at any time before he has completed three months’ service or after the 
completion of the full period of service for which he is engaged, be entitled 
to claim his discharge from the Force by applying to his appointing authority 
through the proper channel.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17A</number> Recoveries 
on resignation and discharge.—A 
member of the Force seeking resignation under rule 16 or discharge under rule 
17 from service shall be required to refund to the Government a sum equal to 
three months pay and allowances received by him or her prior to the resignation 
or discharge, as the case may be, or the cost of training imparted to him or 
her in the Force, whichever is higher.
 
Provided that in the case 
of a member of the force seeking discharge from service under rule 17 within 
the period of three months from the date of enrolment, the sum equal to three 
months pay and allowances shall be calculated with reference to three months 
pay and allowances which would have been received but for discharge:
 
Provided further that a 
member of the Force tendering resignation of seeking discharge from service for 
accepting a job under the Central or State Governments or local bodies, after 
having been granted cadre clearance for the same, shall not be required to 
refund the sum as provided hereinabove.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Discharge 
Certificate.—Every 
member on leaving the Force shall be entitled to a Discharge Certificate in the 
prescribed Form CRP-26.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Travelling allowance 
to men discharged at their own request.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Any member of the Force who claims his discharge on completion of his initial 
period of engagement or any time thereafter shall on being discharged be 
entitled to receive one single railway fare of the class to which he is 
entitled under the rules applicable to servants of the Central Government from 
the place of his discharge to the railway station nearest to his home.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Any member of the 
Force entitled to be discharged at his own request, but who cannot be 
discharged owing to the exigencies of the service, shall retain his title to 
the above concession when the discharge is effected.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Travelling allowance 
admissible to men discharged otherwise than at their own request.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Force discharged otherwise than at his own request shall be 
entitled to a free railway pass of the class to which he is entitled under the 
rules applicable to servant of the Central Government to the railway station 
nearest to his home. In the case of a member of the Force discharged for 
inefficiency the grant of the concession shall be subject to the condition that 
the Commandant is satisfied that the inefficiency is not due to wilful 
negligence. This concession shall not be admissible to a person discharged for 
misconduct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Commandant may, where he considers it 
necessary to do so for the purpose of maintaining and preserving discipline in 
the Unit or Sub-Unit to which the member released from the Quarter Guard 
belongs, make an exception and issue a free railway pass to such member as 
mentioned in sub-rule (1).
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Travelling allowance 
admissible to members of his family in the event of member of the Force being 
declared medically unfit.—If 
a member of the Force has his family residing at a place which is the 
headquarters of the Force prior to his having been declared a medically unfit 
he shall also be entitled to a free railway pass of the same class to which he 
is entitled for each and every member of his family (as defined in Fundamental 
Rules), from the headquarters of the Force to the railway station nearest to 
his home.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Legal Privileges and 
Powers of member of the Force.—Regular 
Army Officers appointed to the Force shall be entitled to all the legal 
privileges enjoyed by Police Officer.
</article> 
  if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endif if !vml endifThe CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Organisation.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The organisation of the Battalion shall be as follows:
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  Head Quarters Company.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  Four service Companies or more 
as sanctioned by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> Head Quarters 
Company—The Head Quarters Company shall be composed of the following:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  Administrative;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  Quarter Master’s Branch;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  Educational;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number>  Transport;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number>  Training; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number>  Tear Smoke platoon.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> The strength of the 
plantoon shall be as follows:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  Administrative Platoon:
 
              1  Commandant
 
              1  Assistant Commandant, 
(Second-in-Command)
 
              1  Subedar Major (Inspector)
 
              2  Sub-Inspector for Civil 
Investigation and police Liaison
 
              3  Head Constables
 
              3  Naiks
 
              1  Lance Naik
 
             29  Constables
 
             41
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Quarter Master’s Platoon:
 
              1  Quarter Master (Deputy 
Superintendent)
 
              1  Sub-Inspector
 
              5  Head Constables
 
              5  Naiks
 
              1  Lance Naik
 
             33  Constables
 
             46
 
This Branch includes 
Technicians Section and Lines Police and Hygiene Section.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Educational Platoon:
 
              1  Sub-Inspector
 
              3  Head Constables
 
              4  Naiks
 
              1  Constable
 
              9
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Transport Platoon:
 
              2  Sub-Inspector includes M.M.
 
              5  Head Constables
 
             16  Naiks
 
              5  Lance Naiks
 
             36  Constables
 
             64
 
It contains workshop 
staff, mechanic and motor drivers.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number> Deleted
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number> Training Platoon:
 
              1  Asstt. Commandant 
(Adjutant)
 
              1  Sub-Inspector
 
              9  Head Constables
 
              6  Naiks
 
              3  Lance Naiks
 
              8  Constables
 
             46  Recruits
 
             74
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>7</number> Two Tear Smoke Platoons:
 
              2  Sub-Inspectors
 
              4  Head Constables
 
              2  Naiks
 
              4  Lance Naiks
 
             40  Constables
 
             52
 
The Head Quarters Company 
shall, ordinarily be commanded by the Assistant Commandant.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Primary Duties of the 
Force.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Members of the Force may be employed in any part of Indian Union for the 
restoration and maintenance of law and order, and for any other purpose as 
directed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Superior Officers and 
other Police Officers, on deputation with the Force, shall ordinarily not be 
employed on work connected with the investigation or prosecution of cases. If 
and when these officers are employed on the duties they shall normally be 
relieved of the command of companies or detachments and the approval of the 
Deputy Inspector General shall be obtained. 
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Standard of Training.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The Deputy Inspector General shall issue a manual prescribing the standard of 
training.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The training shall 
include the following subjects:—
 <subsection>
         <number>1</number>  Correct wearing of uniform 
i.e. clothing and accoutrements.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>2</number>  Ceremonial Drill and Guard 
mounting.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>3</number>  Squad, Platoon, Company and 
Battalion Drill and extended order movements.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>4</number>  Weapon Training including Tear 
Smoke and Riot Drill.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>5</number>  Physical Training.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>6</number>  Education and Elementary Law.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>7</number>  Intelligence Course.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>8</number>  General Police duties excluding 
investigation and prosecution.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>9</number>  Wireless and Motor Transport.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>10</number>  Any other subject which may be 
considered desirable to be introduced in the Force.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> The Commandant may 
depute any member of the Force to undergo a course of training or instruction 
having a bearing on the Central Reserve Police Force work conducted by the 
Central Government or the State Government or by any training establishment of 
the Reserve Police Force or Army Institution or Directorate of Co-ordination 
(Police Wireless) or any other institution:
 
Provided that in the case 
of Sub-Inspectors, Inspectors (Subedars) and Gazetted Officers, the Commandant 
shall obtain the prior permission of the Deputy Inspector General, the 
Inspector General and the Central Government respectively.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The period of 
training shall be treated as duty for the purposes of F.R. 9(6)(b)(i).
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>27B</number> Responsibilities of 
Members of the Force during suspension.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of the Force shall not by reason of his suspension cease to be a 
member of the Force, during the period of his suspension, the powers vested in 
him as such member shall be in abeyance, but he shall be subject to the same 
responsibilities, discipline and penalties to which he would have been subject 
if he were on duty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such member 
shall during the period of his suspension stay at Battalion Headquarters or 
Detachment Headquarters as the Commandant or suspending authority may direct:
 
Provided that the 
Commandant or suspending authority may, for special reasons, grant permission 
in writing to the member to stay elsewhere.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A member under 
suspension shall deposit his arms and belt, if any, with the Quarter Master or 
suspending authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A member under 
suspension shall not be employed on guard duty or any such duty which might 
entail exercise of his power as a member of the Force, nor shall be issued arms 
and ammunition. He shall not be detailed as motor transport driver or signal 
operator.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A member of the Force 
under suspension shall be allowed reasonable facilities for the preparation of 
his defence.]
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Every subordinate officer or every officer of any other rank below him 
including an enrolled follower against whom an order 

1[under serial 
numbers 1 to 7 of the table in rule 27] or under clauses (d) and (e) of section 
13 is passed is entitled to prefer one appeal against such order to the 
Inspector-General; if the original order was passed by the Deputy 
Inspector-General and to the Deputy Inspector-General; if the original order 
was passed by the Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> No appeal shall lie 
against an order by the competent authority inflicting any of the punishments 
mentioned in—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  

1[Serial Nos. 8 to 11 of the Table in 
rule 27;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  Clauses (a), (b) and (c) of 
section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  Against an order discharging 
recruit before the termination of his period of training.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> Every appeal 
preferred under these rules shall contain all material statements and arguments 
relied upon by the person preferring the appeal. It shall contain no 
disrespectful or improper language or irrelevant allegations and it shall be 
complete in itself. Petitions or appeals filed by members of the Force are not 
chargeable with stamp duty. Copies of other documents filed with the appeal 
shall be stamped under section 6 of the Court Fees Act, 1870, unless they have 
to be stamped under article 24 of Schedule I of the Indian Stamp Act, 1899.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Every appeal, whether 
the appellant is still in the Force or not, shall be preferred through the 
Commandant and shall not be sent direct to the appellate authority.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> An appeal which is 
not filed within 30 days of the date of the original order, exclusive of the 
time taken to obtain a copy of the order or record, shall be barred by 
limitation:
 
Provided the appellate 
authority may entertain time barred appeal if deemed fit;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> The Commandant may 
withhold an appeal to the Inspector-General or to the Deputy Inspector General 
in cases—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  where under these rules no 
appeal lies;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  where the appeal does not comply 
with the provisions of sub-rules (c),(d) or (e) above;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  Where it is a further appeal 
presented after a final decision has been given by the competent appellate 
authority and no new facts have been brought out necessitating reconsideration 
of the case:
 
Provided that in every 
case in which an appeal is withheld the person preferring the appeal shall be 
informed of the fact together with brief reasons therefor;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>g</number> No appeal shall lie 
against an order withholding of an appeal by a competent authority:
 
Provided that in cases of 
failure to comply with the conditions stated in sub-rule (c) or (d) above, the 
appeal shall not be withheld if it is preferred again in the prescribed form in 
conformity with the rules and is not time barred.
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> A quarterly statement 
of all appeals withheld with brief reasons in respect of each appeal shall be 
furnished by the Commandant to the Deputy Inspector General.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Revision.—
<section><number>a</number> 
A member of the Force whose appeal has been rejected by a competent authority 
may prefer petition for revision to the next Superior Authority. The power of 
revision may be exercised only when in consequence of some material 
irregularity, there has been injustice or miscarriage of justice or fresh 
evidence is disclosed.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The procedure 
prescribed for appeals under sub-rules (c) to (g) of rule 28 shall apply 
mutatis mutandis to petitions for revision.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> 

1[The next 
superior authority] while passing orders on a revision petition may at its 
discretion enhance punishment:
 
Provided that before 
enhancing the punishment the accused shall be given an opportunity to show 
cause why his punishment should not be enhanced:
 

1[Provided further 
that an order enhancing the punishment shall, for the purpose of appeal, be 
treated as an original order except when the same has been passed by the 
Government in which case no further appeal shall lie, and an appeal against 
such an order shall lie—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  to the Inspector General, if 
the same has been passed by the Deputy Inspector General; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  to the Director General if the 
same has been passed by the Inspector General; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  to the Central Government, if 
the same has been passed by the Director General.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number> 

1[The Director 
General 

2[or Additional 
Director General] or the Inspector-General] or the Deputy Inspector General may 
call for the records of award of any punishment and confirm, enhance, modify or 
annual the same, or make or direct further investigation to be made before 
passing such orders:
 
Provided that in a case 
in which it is proposed to enhance punishment, the accused shall be given an 
opportunity to show cause either orally or in writing as to why his punishment 
should not be enhanced.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Petitions.—A 
subordinate Officer or an officer of any other rank below him including an 
enrolled follower who has any grievance may present a petition subject to the 
condition that it should be addressed to the officer of the lowest rank who is 
empowered to pass the desired order.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Desertion and Absence 
without leave.—
<section><number>a</number> 
If a member of the force who becomes liable for trial under clause (f) of 
section 9, or clause (m) of section 10 or for deserting the Force while not on 
active duty under clause (p) of section 10 read with clause (f) of section 9, 
does not return of his own free will or is not apprehended within sixty days of 
the commencement of the desertion, absence or overstayal of leave, then the 
Commandant shall assemble a court of Inquiry consisting of atleast one Gazetted 
Officer and two other members who shall be either superior or subordinate 
officers to inquire into the desertion, absence or overstayal of leave of the 
offender and such other matters as may be brought before them.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The court of Inquiry 
shall record evidence and its findings. The court’s record shall be admissible 
in evidence in any subsequent proceedings taken against the absentee.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The Commandant shall 
then publish in the Force Order the findings of the Court of Enquiry and the 
absentee shall be declared a deserter from the Force from the date of his 
illegal absence, but he shall not thereby cease to belong to the Force. This 
shall, however be no bar to enlisting another man in the place of a deserter.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Orderly Room.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Report of petty cases of misconduct and indiscipline should as far as possible 
be inquired into and disposed off in Orderly Room by an officer authorised to 
award petty punishment under sub-section (3) of section 11 read with rule 27 to 
any member of the Force who is for the time being subject to his authority. 
Inquiries in the Orderly Room shall be held on two or more fixed days in a 
week.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the offence calls 
for more severe punishment than the officer dealing with it is authorised to 
inflict, he shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  if at Headquarters, have the 
accused brought before the Commandant;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  if away from Headquarters 
forward the record with his recommendations to the Commandant for orders;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  proceedings of such inquiries 
shall be recorded in the Orderly Room Register.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Entry of Punishment 
in Service Roll.—A 
punishment whether judicial or departmental shall be entered in the service 
roll of the offender.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Report on Judicial 
Proceedings.—The 
Commandant shall submit a brief to the Deputy Inspector General on every case 
in which a Member of the Force has been convicted by a Court of Law.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>35</number> Loss or 
Damage to Arms, Ammunition and Property.— 

<section><number>1</number> In all cases of loss or serious damage to arms, ammunition or other 
Government property, where such loss or damage exceeds Rs. 100 in the case of 
arms and ammunition, and Rs. 500 in the case of other Government property, the 
Commandant shall assemble a Court of Inquiry consisting of the Assistant 
Commandant (if available) or the senior superior officer present as the 
president and two superior or subordinate officers as members.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The court shall 
inquire into the case, record evidence and submit findings in Form A.F.A. 2 to 
the Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of the 
findings under sub-rule (2), the Commandant may, if the total value of the loss 
or damage does not exceed Rs. 1000 pass orders that the loss or damage be 
written off.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the total value of 
the loss exceeds Rs. 1000 but does not exceed Rs. 2000 the Commandant shall 
submit the findings to the Deputy Inspector General of Police who may pass 
orders for writing off such loss or damage.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the total value of 
the loss exceeds Rs. 2000, the Commandant shall submit the findings through the 
Deputy Inspector General of Police to the Inspector General of Police or the 
Director General, as the case may be, within the competence of such authority, 
as provided for in the Delegation of Financial powers rules or other orders as 
may be notified from time to time, who may pass orders for writing off such 
loss or damage.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In case of loss or 
damage to arms and ammunition or other Government property where such loss or 
damage does not exceed Rs. 100 in the case of arms and ammunition and Rs. 500 
in the case of other Government property, it shall be dealt with the Commandant 
in the orderly room after a summary enquiry by a Gazetted officer.”
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Judicial Trials.—
<section><number>a</number> 
All trials in relation to any one of the offences specified in section 9 or 10 
shall be held in accordance with the procedure laid down in the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 18981.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> All persons sentenced 
to imprisonment under the Act shall be confined in the nearest jail. Provided 
that if the sentence of imprisonment is for one month or less, “or where the 
Commandant is satisfied that due to the difficulty of transport and escort of 
the person sentenced to imprisonment, to the nearest jail, it is so desirable.” 
Such persons shall be confined in the Quarter Guard of the Force.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>36A</number> Prescribed 
Authority with reference to the proviso to sub-section (2) of Section 16.—For 
the purpose of the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 16, the authority who 
may direct inquiry into, or trial of an offence by an ordinary criminal court 
referred to in that proviso shall be the Commandant.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36B</number> Definition.—For 
the purpose of this Chapter, “Magistrate” means a Magistrate other than the 
Commandant or an Assistant Commandant on whom the powers of a Magistrate have 
been conferred under sub-section (2) of section 16.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>36DD</number> Language 
to be used in proceeding before Commandants and Assistant Commandants.—Either 
English or Hindi may be used by the Commandants or Assistant Commandants while 
exercising the powers of a Magistrate under sub-section (2) of section 16 for 
the purpose of inquiring into or trying any offence.
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36E</number> Magistrate not to 
try persons subject to the Act.—Where 
a person subject to the Act is brought before a Magistrate and charged with an 
offence referred to in the main paragraph of sub-section (2) of section 16 for 
which he is liable to be tried such Magistrate shall not proceed to inquire 
into or try the offence unless—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> he is of opinion for reasons to 
be recorded that he should so proceed without being moved thereto by the 
Commandant; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> he is moved thereto by the 
Commandant.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36F</number> Magistrate to give 
notice.—Before 
proceedings under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 36E, the Magistrate shall give written 
notice to the Commandant and until the expiry of a period of twenty-one days 
from the date of the service of such notice he shall not—
 </section><section>
       <number>a</number> convict or acquit the accused 
under section 243, section 245, section 247 or section 248 of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)1, 
or hear him in defence under section 244 of the said Code; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> frame in writing a charge against 
the accused under section 251A, or section 254 of the said Code; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> make an order committing the 
accused for trial by the High Court or the Court of Sessions under section 207A 
or section 213 of said Code; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> transfer the case for enquiry or 
trial under section 192 of the said Code.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>36H</number> Magistrate to be 
informed of the trial of the accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When an accused person has been delivered by the Magistrate, the Commandant or 
Assistant Commandant, as the case may be, shall, as soon as may, inform the 
Magistrate whether the accused has been tried by him or any other effectual 
proceedings have been taken ordered to be taken against the accused or not.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the Magistrate 
has been informed under sub-rule (1) that the accused has not been tried or 
other effectual proceedings have not been taken or ordered to be taken against 
him, the Magistrate shall report the circumstances to the State Government 
which may in consultation with the Central Government take appropriate steps to 
ensure that the accused person is dealt with in accordance with law.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>36J</number> Commandant 
to deliver the accused to the Magistrate.—Where 
a person subject to the Act has committed an offence which in the opinion of 
the Commandant is to be tried by a Magistrate in accordance with the law in 
force, the Commandant shall after giving written notice to the Magistrate 
concerned deliver such person under proper escort to the Magistrate.]]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Character and Service 
Roll.—The 
Commandant shall maintain—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> Character and Service Roll in 
Form CRP-2 for each Subordinate Officer, Under Officer and Constable.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> Service Roll in Form C.A.C.-10-C 
for each enrolled follower. Form CRP-I shall also be attached to the Service 
Roll of each enrolled followers.
</section></article> 
 The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE 
 RULES, 1955
  
 <article><number>38</number> <title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]</title>
  
  


</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> System of Accounts.—The 
accounts of the Force shall be maintained in accordance with the rules 
contained in the Uttar Pradesh Police Manual. The contingent and other charges 
pertaining to the Forces are subject to the provisions of the Chapter and 
Appendix relating to contingencies in the General Financial Rules. All 
transactions shall be subject to the audit of the Accountant General concerned.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Scale of pay and 
allowances.—The 
existing rates of pay and allowances are as shown in Appendices D and E.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Free Accommodation.—All 
members of the Force other than superior officers who are required to reside at 
or near the place of their duty for the proper discharge of duty, shall be 
provided with rent free accommodation or house or house rent allowance in lieu 
thereof limited to the actual amount or house rent paid by the member concerned 
subject to a maximum of 10 per cent of pay, and subject to the condition that 
they engage accommodation which in the opinion of the controlling authority is 
conveniently near to the premises in which their regular duties have to be 
performed.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Pension.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Pensions and gratuities for service in the Force shall be regulated according 
to the provisions contained in Chapters XV to XXI and XLVII and XLVIII of the 
Civil Service Regulation as may be amended from time to time and the new 
Pension Rules promulgated in the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance 
Memorandum No. F.3(1)E (Spl)/47, dated the 17th April,1950 as may be amended 
from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Pensions and 
gratuities to enrolled followers for service in the Force shall be governed by 
provisions contained in the Central (Class IV) Services (Gratuity, Pension and 
Retirement) Rules, 1936 and the New Pension Rules published in the Government 
of India in the Ministry of Finance Memorandum No. F.3(1)E(Spl)/47, dated the 
17the April, 1950, as may be amended from time to time.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Superannuation.—1[
<section><number>a</number> 
Retirement of a member of the Force shall take effect from the afternoon of the 
last day of the month in which such member attains the 

2[age of 57 
years]. In case, the date of birth of a member of the Force falls on the first 
day of a month, his retirement shall take effect from the afternoon of the last 
day of the month preceding the month in which the member of Force attains the


2[age of 55 
years.]
 

3[(b) the 
provisions of clause (a) shall not be applicable to a member of the Force who 
is on extension in service on the date of coming into force of the Central 
Reserve Police Force (Amendment) Rules, 1998.]
 
Provided further in all 
such cases prior approval of the Government in the case of superior officers, 
of the Inspector-General in the case of Subordinate as well as the Under 
Officers and of the Deputy Inspector General in the case of other Members of 
the Force except enrolled followers in whose case approval of the Commandant 
shall be obtained. 
 

4[(c) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this rule—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the appointing authority shall, 
if it is of opinion that it is in the public interest to do so, have absolute 
right to retire any member of the Force who has attained the age of 50 years or 
put in 25 years of qualifying service, by giving him notice of not less than 
three months in writing or three months pay and allowance in lieu of such 
notice,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  any member of the force, may, 
by giving notice of not less than three months in writing to the appointing 
authority, retire from service after he has attained the age of 50 years or put 
in 25 years of qualifying service.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number> (i) any member of the 
Force who has put in not less than 20 years of qualifying service may, by 
giving notice of not less than three months in writing to the appointing 
authority, retire from service voluntarily and unless the exigencies of service 
require otherwise, he shall be permitted to retire.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> the benefit of 
retiring person shall be admissible to members of the Force retiring under 
clause (i);
 

5[(iii) a notice 
of less than three months may also be accepted by the appointing authority in 
appropriate cases on the condition that the Government servant shall not apply 
for commutation of a part of his pension before the expiry of the period of 
notice of three months.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> a notice of 
voluntary retirement may be withdrawn with the approval of the appointing 
authority, provided the request for such withdrawal is made before the expiry 
of the period of notice.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> before a member of 
the Force gives notice of voluntary retirement with reference to this sub-rule, 
he should satisfy himself by means of a reference to the appropriate 
administrative authority that he has, in fact completed 20 years of service 
qualifying for pension.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number> a notice to retire 
voluntarily under clause (i) after completion of 20 years of qualifying service 
shall require acceptance by the appointing authority if the date of retirement 
on the expiry of the period notice would be earlier than the date on which the 
member of the Force concerned could have retired under sub-rule (a). Such 
acceptance may be generally given in all cases except where;
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number> any disciplinary proceedings are 
pending or contemplated against the member of the Force concerned for the 
imposition of a major penalty and the disciplinary authority, having regard to 
the circumstances of the case, is of the view that the imposition of the 
penalty of removal or dismissal from the service would be warranted in the 
case; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>b</number> any prosecution is contemplated 
or may have been launched in a court of law against the member of the Force 
concerned:
 
Provided that—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> in cases, referred to in item 
(a) and item (b) above, approval of the Government in the case of Superior 
Officers, of the Inspector General in the case of Subordinate and under 
officers, of the Deputy Inspector General in the case of other members of the 
Force except enrolled followers and of the Commandant in the case of enrolled 
followers shall be obtained;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> in other cases, acceptance by 
the appointing authority may be presumed and the retirement of the member of 
the Force concerned may take effect in the terms of the notice, unless the 
appointing authority passes an order to the contrary before the expiry of the 
period of notice.
 

6[***].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number> The weightage 
admissible under 

5[clause (i) of 
sub-rule (e)] shall only be an addition to the qualifying service for purpose 
of pension and gratuity, but shall not entitle the member of the Force retiring 
voluntarily to any notional fixation of pay for purpose of determining the 
pension and gratuity based on the actual emoluments calculated with reference 
to the date of retirement.]
 

7[(e)(i) The 
qualifying service as on the date of intended retirement of a member of the 
force retiring under rule 43(c) (ii) or rule 43(d) (i) with or without 
permission shall be increased by the period not exceeding five years, subject 
to the conditions that the total qualifying service rendered by him does not in 
any case exceed thirty three years and it does not take him beyond the date of 
superannuation.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> The weightage of 
five years under clause (i) shall not be admissible in cases of those members 
of the Force who are prematurely retired in the public interest under rule 
43(c)(i).]
 
Explanation I.—“Qualifying 
service” means service rendered while on duty or otherwise, which shall be 
taken into account for the purpose of pension or gratuity admissible under the 
retirement rules.
 
Explanation II.—In 
computing the period of three month of notice referred to in sub-rules (c) and 
(d), the date of service of the notice and the date of it expiry shall be 
excluded.
 
comment
 
The appellant was aggrieved by the view 
taken by the High Court fixing the superannuation age of the respondent, who 
was re-employed after retirement from the Army, at 58, overlooking the terms 
and conditions of the order of employment. The Supreme Court held that the High 
Court was not right, as the contract of employment specifically refers to CRPF 
Rules, 1955 which covers the retirement age as well; Union of India v.
B.D. Pandey, AIR 1999 SC 546.
 
 










</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Special pay.—If 
any member of the Force has rendered exemplary and outstanding service, any 
special pay earned by him during the period of his service in the Force, may be 
treated wholly or partly as emoluments for the purpose of Pension in accordance 
with the order sanctioning the special pay. In the absence of any specific 
mention to that effect in the order sanctioning the special pay, the case shall 
be referred for orders to the Government who shall decide each case on its own 
merits.
 
(Special pay for pay 
fixation on promotion is governed by Government of India’s decision No. 2 below 
F.R. 19(2) Article 486A of the Civil Service Regulations governs counting for 
pension).
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Officiating pay.—The 
pay of the members of the Force officiating in the rank or grade other than 
their substantive appointment shall be regulated in accordance with the 
Fundamental Rules as may be amended from time to time.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Pay and allowance on 
detachments and under training.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Subject to conditions set forth against items 1 and 2 of Appendix B, advance of 
travelling allowance and pay may be granted by the Commandant to members of the 
Force when proceedings on detachment duty.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> All ranks shall be 
entitled to draw travelling allowance under the Supplementary Rules as amended 
from time to time when proceeding to or returning from duty. Railway warrants 
shall be used by all ranks upto the rank of Subedar (Inspector).
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> While on duty all 
ranks shall draw daily allowance under Supplementary Rule 51 read with 
Supplementary rules 71 and 73 subject to the provision that normally daily 
allowance shall be reduced to 3/4 rates after the first 10 days and to half 
rates after the next 20 days.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The Inspector General 
is competent to define the limits of the sphere of duty of any detachment sent 
outside the Headquarters of the Force or to fix the entire area of a State (as 
defined in the Constitution of India) or part of a State as the temporary 
Headquarters of a detachment posted outside the Headquarters.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> Whenever, a 
detachment of the Force is sent out to a station away from the Headquarters of 
the Force with the result that it requires arrangement for the encashment of 
bills for the pay, allowances, etc., of the members of the detachment 
from the Government Treasury nearest to the place where the detachment is 
stationed, a reference may be made through proper channel to the Government of 
India in the Ministry of Home Affairs so that arrangements for such encashment 
may be made, in case no other satisfactory arrangements are feasible.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> In accordance with 
the Supplementary Rule 164, all ranks shall draw daily allowance at the under 
mentioned rates, while deputed to undergo a course of training or instruction:—
 
GAZETTED AND SUBORDINATE 
OFFICERS
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>          At full rate 
for the first ten days.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>          At 3/4th 
rate for the next twenty days.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number>          At 1/2 rate 
for the rest of the period.
 
ALL OTHERS
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> At full rate of the 
entire period of their stay.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Free transport on 
enlistment.—On 
enrolment, a member of the Force is entitled to a free railway pass from the 
railway station nearest to his home or place of enrolment to Headquarters of 
the Force.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Recruit’s subsistence 
allowance.—A 
consolidated allowance not exceeding Rs. 6 may be paid by the enrolling officer 
to recruiter for each recruit produced for enlistment. The payment is intended 
to cover the travelling expenses of the recruiter, and the recruit and the 
subsistence allowance of the recruit, upto the time of the recruit’s approval 
or rejection. This is not a reward, and is subject to the recruit being of the 
required standard, and the actual expense being incurred.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Death of member of 
Force.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
In the event of a member of the Force dying while on duty the members of his 
family shall, besides the fares, for their transport to their home town, be 
also eligible to transfer grant and transfer incidentals, including the actual 
cost of transporting the personal effects and conveyance of the same rate as 
are admissible to a Government servant on transfer under S.R. 116.]
 

2[(2) The 
Government shall also pay, subject to the maximum limit of Rs. 250 (Rupees two 
hundred fifty), funeral expenses when any member of the Force (other than 
superior officer) dies at the headquarters of the Force or on active duty.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Former military 
service and military pensions.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Save as herein otherwise provided the pay, allowances and pensions of 
ex-service officers and man who obtain employment in the Force after being 
given a military pension or gratuity or bonus shall be regulated by the 
appropriate rule of the Civil Service Regulations as may be amended from time 
to time.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> When a military 
pension has been granted the pay and allowances in the Force shall be regulated 
under article 526 Civil Service Regulations as may be amended from time to 
time, or any other orders of the Government of India which may be issued in 
this regard. The officers and men shall continue to draw their military 
pensions and their previous military service shall not count towards civil 
pension. If the military pension of a person does not exceed Rs. 15 a month it 
shall not be taken into account in fixing his pay and allowance in the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> In the case of men 
who have not earned a monthly military pension but are fully trained, the 
initial pay as constable may be fixed at a stage not exceeding Rs. 40 in the 
scale of Rs. 35-1-50.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Men who were 
discharged from Army before earning a pension for their military service but 
receive bonus or gratuity in lieu shall count their Military Service towards 
Civil Pension :
 
Provided that the bonus 
or gratuity is refunded in such number of monthly instalments not normally 
exceeding 36 and beginning from such dates as may be determined:
 
Provided further that no 
instalment other than the final one should be less than Rs. 3.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> In the case of men 
who may be discharged from the Force before the gratuity or bonus is recovered 
in full, the balance outstanding should be recovered either in a lump sum or in 
suitable instalments from the gratuity or pension as the case may be, that may 
be sanctioned for the combined military and civil service.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> Men who received 
neither a monthly pension, a bonus nor gratuity shall count their approved 
military service towards civil pension after three years satisfactory service 
in the force.
 
Note.—“Pension” 
in this clause includes the pension equivalent of gratuity or any other form of 
retirement benefit.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Wound, injury or 
family pension or gratuities.—All 
members of the Force on duty or on duty with a military force shall be entitled 
to wound, injury or family pensions or gratuities as laid down in Civil Service 
Regulations or the Central Civil Service (Extraordinary Pension) Rules, 1939 as 
may be amended from time to time.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Financial powers.—The 
financial powers of the Commandant as well as of Officer Commanding Detachments 
are given in Appendix B.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>53A</number> Rewards.—The 
following principles shall govern the grant of rewards to the members of the 
Force: Rewards shall be granted only to officers and men of and below the rank 
of Subedar (Inspector) for—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> doing outstanding work requiring 
special courage, skill or initiative such as recapture of an escaped prisoner 
or life convicts, the arrest of a wanted criminal or in connection with the 
securing of information leading to the arrest of hostile elements or in an 
encounter with hostile elements or criminals, etc;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> doing work of a less outstanding 
nature but requiring prompt, honest and intelligent observance of, and 
obedience to, orders so as to be of material assistance in any manoeuvre or 
operation;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> extra hard work in connection 
with a big operation against hostile or lawless elements; and
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> in exceptional cases, for 
smartness diligence, praiseworthy attention to the public or for any other 
purpose which in the opinion of the officers competent to grant the reward is 
calculated to promote the efficiency of the Force.
 
   Note.—(i)  
“General good work” shall not be a ground for the grant of reward;
 <subsection>
            <number>ii</number> Orders sanctioning reward 
should indicate the reasons for which they are granted. The clause or clauses 
of this rule under which they are granted should also be mentioned in the order 
sanctioning the rewards;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number> Rewards shall not be 
sanctioned on request.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Force deductions.—The 
Commandant is authorised to make deductions from amounts due to members of the 
Force in satisfaction of money owed by them to messing and other funds of the 
Force, provided that members of the Force are not asked to make any new 
contributions without the prior approval of the Inspector General.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Merit.—
<section><number>a</number> 
All promotions shall be governed by merit. Other things being equal seniority 
shall count for promotion. For promotion, a member of the Force must be 
qualified and recommended by the Commandant, Assistant Commandant or Company 
Commander as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> For exceptional 
reasons, the Commandant may promote an unqualified Head Constable to the rank 
of Sub-Inspector or an unqualified Sub-Inspector to the rank of Subedar 
(Inspector) with the prior approval of the Deputy Inspector General or 
Inspector General respectively, provided that such promotions in either case do 
not exceed ten per cent of the sanctioned strength in such ranks.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Seniority.—Ordinarily 
a senior member of the Force who is qualified and recommended shall be 
promoted. Any member of the Force having unsatisfactory record either from the 
point of view of work or conduct, may be suspended. On the other hand, any 
member of the Force having exceptional qualification may be given accelerated 
promotion out of turn.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Determination of 
Seniority 

1[of Members of 
the Force other than the Gazetted Officers].—Seniority 
shall depend on the date of confirmation in each rank; provided that a person 
whose period of probation is extended for the reason that he is not qualified 
and provided further that this non-qualification is due to circumstances beyond 
his control, shall retain his seniority according to the date of his promotion 
to a rank in a clear vacancy, if he attains the necessary qualifications at the 
earliest available opportunity.
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Probationary period.—An 
officer promoted in permanent vacancy shall be on probation for one year in the 
rank to which promoted. He may be reverted at any time during the probationary 
period but, if not reverted shall ordinarily be confirmed on conclusion of the 
probationary period. In special circumstances the probationary period may be 
extended by the officer authorised to order the promotion. Confirmation shall 
count from the date on which a member of the Force is promoted on probation in 
a clear vacancy.
 
IGP CRP’s Order No.O. III-9/63, dated 1st 
February, 1965
 
In view of the 
instructions contained in the office Memorandum No. F.I/10/64 Estt(d), dated 
the 14th January, 1965, of the Ministry of Home Affairs, it is stressed that 
the Competent authorities for confirmation and promotion in the CRP should 
ensure that every officer or man or clerk to be considered for promotion or 
confirmation is upright and honest.
 
IGP CRP’s No.C.VI-I/64-65,dated 7th October, 
1965 and 27th October, 1965
 
Temporary/officiating 
service, in a rank may be counted as probationary period, if the service is 
satisfactory.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number>Officiating 
promotions.—Officiating 
promotions in temporary vacancies (e.g. Leave and Deputation) may be 
made, if required by the exigencies of service. Normally, such promotions shall 
be made from amongst persons who have already been approved for promotion.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
The following 
examinations and courses shall be held to enable Under Officers and Constables 
to qualify for promotion:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number> From Head Constable to 
Sub-Inspector
 
              Ist Class Certificate of 
Education, and Third Class English Certificate.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> From Naik to Head Constable
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number> Senior Cadre Course, and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number> Second Class Certificate of 
Education.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>3</number> From Constable to Naik:
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number> Junior Cadre Course, and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number> Third Class Certificate of 
Education.
 
Note.—1[Member 
of the Force with Matriculation or equivalent of higher academic qualification 
from a recognised Board or University shall be exempted from passing any of the 
above mentioned examination.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Maintenance of lists 
of approved candidates.—Lists 
of approved candidates for promotion to various ranks, required to be 
maintained under sub-rule (b) of rule 62, shall be kept in the office of the 
Commandant, and promotions shall ordinarily be made from these lists according 
to the provisions of rule 55.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Preparation of lists 
of approved candidates.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The Commandant may, for special reasons, promote to the next higher rank any 
qualified candidate whose name is not on the appropriate approved list. In the 
case of Subedar (Inspectors) and sub-Inspectors prior approval of the Inspector 
General and the Deputy Inspector General respectively shall be obtained.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Promotions shall be 
made from among the best men in the Force as a whole and for this purpose the 
Commandant shall maintain separate lists for promotion to different ranks, as 
shown below:
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> List “A” containing names of 
Constables fit for promotion to the rank of Lance Naik.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  List “B” containing names of 
Lance Naiks suitable for promotion to the rank of Naik.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  List “C” containing names of 
Naiks suitable for promotion to the rank of Head Constables.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number>  List “D” containing names of 
suitable Head Constables for promotion to the rank of Sub-Inspectors.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number>  List “E” containing names of 
suitable Sub-Inspectors for promotion to the rank of Subedars (Inspectors).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> Ordinarily, only 
those men shall be considered for inclusion in List “A” who have passed the 
prescribed course for Drill Instructors and are sufficiently educated to be 
able to read and write Hindi, Roman and Hindi numerals. Higher educational 
qualification is necessary for promotion above the rank of Head Constable, but 
the normal standard shall be Third Class for promotion from Constable to Lance 
Naik and second class from Naik to Head Constable. A man selected for promotion 
should have initiative, power and leadership the makings of an officer. Men on 
promotion list for Naiks and above shall be on probation for at least one year 
and names of those on the list who do not come upto the required standard shall 
be removed thereof from time to time. Entry of names in lists A,B and C shall 
be made by the Commandant and in Lists D and E by the Commandant with the 
approval of the Deputy Inspector General of Police and Inspector-General of 
Police respectively.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Selection Board.—
In February and August each year the Commandants shall constitute Selection 
Board consisting of himself, Asstt. Commandant and Adjutant and nominate in the 
prescribed form Sub-Inspectors considered fit for promotion to the rank of 
Subedars (Inspectors) and Head Constables considered fit for promotion to the 
rank of Sub-Inspectors. The names of Sub-Inspectors and Head Constables whose 
nominations are accepted by the Deputy Inspector General shall be placed on the 
approved lists, seniority of men brought on these lists shall be determined by 
dates of their selection.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>64</number> Educational 
qualifications for promotion to the Rank of Sub-Inspector.—No 
Head Constable, with academic qualification below matriculation, who has not 
obtained a First class certificate of education and at least a third class 
English certificate shall be nominated for promotion to rank of Sub-Inspector.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Confidential Reports.—In 
February each year the Commandant shall forward to the Deputy Inspector General 
a confidential report in the prescribed form on the work and conduct of each 
and every Sub-Inspector and Head Constable whose names are on the approved 
lists. While recording his report the Commandant shall indicate together with 
reasons in support of his opinion whether he recommends that a name of the 
Member of the Force should remain on the approved list or be removed from it. 
The Deputy Inspector General shall pass orders on these recommendations after 
such inquiries as may deem fit.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Additions to and 
removals from approved lists.—All 
acceptances for and removals from the approved lists shall be published in the 
Force orders.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Head Constables.—Promotions 
to the rank of Head Constable shall be made by the Commandant according to 
seniority from the list “C” referred to in rule 62 subject to the general 
provisions of rule 55 on the recommendations of Company Commanders. The 
requisite qualification for such promotions are the passing of the Senior Cadre 
Course and the possession of the Second Class Certificate of Education 

1[or a 
Matriculation or equivalent or higher academic qualification certificate.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Naiks.—Promotion 
to the rank of Naik shall be made by the Commandant from the list “B” referred 
to in rule 62 subject to the general provisions of rule 55 on the 
recommendation of Company Commanders. The requisite qualifications for such 
promotions are the passing of the Junior Cadre Course and the possession of a 
Third Class Certificate of Education 

1[or a 
Matriculation or equivalent or higher academic qualification certificate.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Lance Naiks.—A 
Lance Naik shall receive the same pay as a Constable. Appointments shall be 
made by the Commandant from the List of Constables qualified for promotion to 
the rank of Naik. Such appointment shall be made on the recommendations of 
Company Commanders. Seniority alone shall not be the guiding factor in making 
such appointments but men who are considered to be potential leaders shall be 
given preference. A Constable appointed to the rank of Lance Naik but found 
unsuitable for the rank may be summarily reverted to the rank of Constable 
without assigning any reasons.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Special promotion to 
Naik and Head Constable.—The 
Commandant may, on the recommendation of a Company Commander, promote to the 
rank of Lance Naik, Naik or Head Constable respectively, a Constable, a Lance 
Naik or a Naik, who, although not qualified for promotion, is considered in all 
respects capable of acting as an Under Officer, provided that the number of 
unqualified Naik and Head Constables permanent and officiating may not at any 
time exceed 10 per cent of the sanctioned number of posts of each rank.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Special qualification 
for promotion.—Qualifications 
as Drill Instructor, Physical Training Instructor, Weapon Training Instructor, 
Tear Smoke Training Instructor or Signalling Instructor etc. shall be 
considered as additional qualifications for promotion.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Withholding of 
increment.— If 
the increment of a member of the Force is withheld, the period for which it is 
withheld and the reason for withholding it, shall be stated in the Force 
Orders. Such period shall not exceed one year.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Subedars (Inspectors) 
and Sub-Inspectors.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Subedars (Inspectors) and Sub-Inspectors are in a time scale of pay; and the 
grant of increment is subject to approved service, efficiency, and good 
conduct. There are efficiency bars at the following stages:—
 
Subedars(Inspectors) at 
Rs. 250 (Rs. 320 in new scale).
 
Sub-Inspectors at Rs. 180 
(Rs. 200 in new scale).
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Increments shall be 
sanctioned by the Commandant, but prior approval of the Deputy Inspector 
General shall be obtained before an Officer is allowed to cross an efficiency 
bar and the fact shall be recorded in the Force Orders.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Head Constables, 
Naiks and Constables.—Increment 
in the time scale of Head Constables, Naiks and Constables shall be sanctioned 
by the Commandant on the recommendation of Company Commanders. Such increments 
shall be sanctioned, subject to approved service, general efficiency and good 
conduct.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> How to be made.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Officiating promotions shall be normally made according to seniority in the 
approved lists, subject to the general provisions of Sections I and II of this 
Chapter and the exigencies of the service.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Commandant shall 
be competent to sanction officiating promotions in the following cases:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> The Sub-Inspectors to Subedars 
(Inspectors) with the approval of the Inspector General.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> From Head Constable to 
Sub-Inspector with the approval of Deputy Inspector General.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> From Naik to Head Constable.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> From Constable and Lance Naik to 
Naik.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number> If the Commandant 
decided to pass over, for officiating promotion, an officer whose name is on 
the appropriate approved list the prior sanction of the Inspector General or 
the Deputy Inspector General, as the case may be, shall be obtained.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Supersession.—The 
passing over of any member of the Force for promotion in an officiating vacancy 
of four months or less (except for inefficiency or misconduct) or on the 
grounds of technical appointment such as Motor Transport Sub-Inspector, Radio 
Sub-Inspector, Armourers, Tailors, Carpenters shall not amount to supersession.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>76A</number> Honorary 
rank of Company Commander/Quarter Master.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, on the recommendation of the Inspector General, 
confer the honorary rank of Company Commander/Quarter Master on senior and 
deserving Subedars and Subedar Major and employ them as such. During such 
employment they would not be entitled to any benefit of pay or travelling and 
other allowances of the post of Company Commander/Quarter Master.]
 

2[(2) They will, 
however, be supplied free of cost the extra articles as shown in item 7 of the 
foot-note below Appendix ‘A’ to be worn as honorary Company Commander/Quarter 
Master in addition to the articles of uniform already issued to them as 
Subedars.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>76B</number> Grant of 
Local Rank.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding, anything contained in the rules, the 
Director General may, subject to confirmation of the Central Government, grant 
to an Officer or an Inspector of the Force a rank, just above in the order of 
seniority from the ranks mentioned below, for a period of six months, which 
may, if necessary, be extended further, in the interest of better functioning 
of the Force, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> Additional Director 
General; (ii) Inspector General; (iii) Deputy Inspector General; (iv) 
Additional Deputy Inspector General; (v) Commandant; (vi) Second-in-Command; 
(vii) Deputy Commandant; (viii) Assistant Commandant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An Officer or 
Inspector of the Force holding a rank under sub-rule (1) shall,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  exercise the command and be 
vested with the powers of an officer holding that rank;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  cease to hold that rank if the 
grant of such rank is not confirmed within one month by the Central Government 
or when so ordered by the Director General or when he ceases to hold the 
appointment for which the rank was granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  not be entitled to claim any 
seniority over other officers of the Force by virtue of having held such rank; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  not be entitled to any extra pay 
and allowances for holding such rank.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Subedar (Inspector) 
Major.—1[
<section><number>a</number> 
The appointment of Subedars (Inspector) Major shall be made by the Head of 
Office with the prior approval of the Director General on the basis of the 
recommendations of a Screening Committee to be constituted by the Director 
General. Selection shall be made on the principle of seniority-cum-fitness and 
the seniority for this purpose shall be combined seniority of Inspectors in the 
Force.]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The appointment shall 
ordinarily be for three years, but may be extended from time to time for a 
period not exceeding one year at a time, unless promoted, until he attains the 
age of superannuation.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The Subedar 
(Inspector) Major ranks as the Senior most Subordinate Officer.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Sub-Inspector 
Adjutant.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The appointment of Sub-Inspector Adjutant shall be made by the Commandant by 
selection from Sub-Inspectors who are good instructors and disciplinarians.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The maximum period of 
the appointment shall not ordinarily exceed three years.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Quarter Master 
Sub-Inspector.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The appointment of Quarter Master Sub-Inspector shall be made by the Commandant 
from amongst Sub-Inspectors with special qualification in this direction.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The maximum period of 
the appointment shall not ordinarily exceed three years.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Head Constables.—All 
special appointments in the rank of Head Constable shall be made by the 
Commandant. The Battalion Havilar Major shall rank as the senior most Head 
Constable, except for purposes of promotion. The maximum period of the 
appointment shall not ordinarily exceed three years.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Nominal roll of the 
Central Reserve Police Force—Particulars.—
<section><number>a</number> 
A nominal roll in the following form shall be maintained for all ranks:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> Serial No.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Name
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Force No.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Caste
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number> Residence
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number> Date of enlistment in the Force
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>7</number> Previous police or Military 
Service
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>8</number> Date of promotion
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>9</number> Present appointment
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>10</number> Educational qualifications
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>11</number> Remarks (here enter details of 
promotion, reduction, etc.)
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> A separate nominal 
roll shall be maintained for Recruit Constables who have not been confirmed.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Order of seniority.—Officers 
shall rank in the order of seniority as determined by the date of confirmation 
and in the case officers officiating from the date of continuous officiating. 
Seniority in the case of constables shall be determined by the date of 
enlistment in the Force.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Maintenance of 
Promotion and Reversion Roll.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Promotion and Reversion Rolls shall be maintained separately for officiating 
and substantive promotions as follows:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> Of Sub-Inspectors to the rank of 
Subedars (Inspectors).
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Of Head Constables to the rank of 
Sub-Inspectors.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Of Naiks to the rank of Head 
Constables.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Of Constables to the rank of 
Naiks.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> The Promotion and 
Reversion Roll shall contain the following particulars:—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> Serial No.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Nature of vacancy.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Date of vacancy.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Commandant’s Orders.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number> Date on which a member of the 
Force was superseded or whose promotion has been withheld and the date on which 
he received a copy of the order.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number> Number and the date of the order 
notifying the promotion or reversion, as the case may be.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>7</number> Remarks.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Incorporation of 
entries in the promotion and reversion rolls.—The 
Promotion and Reversion Rolls shall be maintained by the Establishment Clerk 
who shall make entries in the first three columns and submit for the orders 
with all necessary papers and character rolls to the Commandant whenever any 
promotion of Sub-Inspector to the rank of Subedar (Inspector) or of Head 
Constable to the rank of Sub-Inspector or their reversion falls due. The 
Commandant shall fill up columns 4 and 5 of the roll with his own hand, 
mentioning in column 5 the names of members of the Force superseded, with a 
brief note of the reasons for their supersession. In other cases, the 
Establishment Clerk shall fill up all columns of the rolls. On the first 
occasion of the supersession of the member of the Force, a note to that effect 
together with reasons thereof shall also be made in his character roll and he 
shall be given a copy of the order.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Army officers.—Leave 
of military officers in the Force shall, if their pay has been refixed in 
accordance with the Government of India in the Ministry of Defence’s letter No. 
117/1/SIDCCD 5, dated the 23rd November, 1948, be regulated by the Military 
Leave Rules as contemplated in para 4 of the aforesaid letter. If their pay has 
not been so refixed it shall be regulated in accordance with the provisions of 
Fundamental Rule 100.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Other superior 
officers.—Leave 
shall be admissible under the rules applicable to them in the service to which 
they belong.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>87</number> Other police officers 
on deputation from other services.—Leave 
shall be admissible under the rules applicable to them in the service to which 
they belong.
 
Note.—It 
shall be open to the officers mentioned in rules 85 and 86 to elect, on their 
permanent transfer to the Force or at any time thereafter, the leave rules 
applicable to the Members of the Force on the analogy of the F.R. 93A.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Other superior 
officers and members of the force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provision of sub-rule (2), all superior officers and members of 
the Force, other than those to whom rules 85 to 87 apply, shall be governed by 
the provisions of the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972 for the time 
being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), all superior officers and members of the 
Force other than those to whom rules 85 to 87 apply, shall, while serving in 
any establishment of Central Reserve Police Forces except offices of Director 
General/Inspector Generals/Deputy Inspector Generals, be entitled to 60 days 
earned leave in a calendar year in the following manner:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> The credit to be afforded to the 
leave account of all the personnel as stated in para (2) above in respect of 
earned leave at the commencement of each calendar half year shall be at a 
uniform rate of 30 days.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> The credit to be afforded 
vide (i) above shall be reduced by 1/6 of the period of extra ordinary 
leave only availed of during the previous half year subject to a maximum of 30 
days.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No such earned leave 
shall be accummulated for more than 120.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No such earned leave 
shall be granted for more than 90 days at a time, and
 

1[(5) No second 
Saturdays shall be availed as off days by the executive personnel working in 
units other than the offices of D.G.,I.G. and D.I.G.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>89</number> Leave sanctioning 
authorities.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Any leave, other than special disability leave, admissible under the rules 
shall be granted as follows:
 

        1[(1) to a superior officer 
by the Commandant, after obtaining a report in regard to its admissibility from 
the audit officer and to the Commandant by the Deputy Inspector General.]
 <subsection>
       <number>2</number> to members of the Force other 
than superior officers at the discretion of the Commandant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> Casual leave.—(1) 
Casual leave to superior officers shall not exceed fifteen days in any one 
calendar year, subject to the condition that not more than ten day’s casual 
leave may be allowed at any one time. This condition may, however, be waived in 
individual cases if there are exceptional circumstances justifying a relaxation 
in this regard. This leave shall be granted by the Deputy Inspector General in 
the case of Commandant and by the Commandant in the case of other superior 
officers of the Force.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in clause (3), the Commandant and the Company Commander may grant 
casual leave not exceeding fifteen days in any one calendar year to any member 
of the Force working under them subject to the condition that not more than ten 
days casual leave may be allowed at any one time. The Head of Office may, 
however, waive this condition in individual cases if he considers that there 
are exceptional circumstances justifying a relaxation in this regard.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> In the case of those 
members of the Force who require more than five days to complete the onward and 
return journeys to their homes, the maximum period of casual leave admissible 
in any one calendar year may be enhanced in accordance with the following 
scale:—
 
 
Number 
of days required to complete   Maximum number of days casual 
 
       
both onward and return journeys         leave in one calendar year
 

                        6 days                                     16 days
 

                        7 days                                     17 days
 

                        8 days                                     18 days
 

                        9 days                                     19 days
 

                        10 days                                    20 days
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> Casual leave cannot 
be combined with any other kind of leave. 

2[In no case shall 
holidays or off days be counted as part of casual leave.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> The special 
disability leave to any member of the Force may be granted by the Government in 
accordance with the provisions of the Fundamental rule 83 read with serial No. 
26 of Appendix 4 thereof.
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>90</number> Recall from leave.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Members of the Force on leave may be recalled at any time by authority 
empowered to sanction their leave.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> They may be directed 
to report for duty either at headquarters or to proceed direct to the place at 
which their services are required.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> In either case they 
will be entitled to travelling allowance as on tour (by the shortest route) for 
the return journey. If a free railway pass is in the possession of a member of 
the Force and it can be used for the return journey, it should be so used. In 
that case, member of the Force will be entitled to the balance if any of the 
travelling allowance admissible. If the pass cannot be utilised, it should be 
surrendered whereupon it shall lapse. The member of the Force concerned in that 
case will be entitled to the full travelling allowance admissible.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>91</number> Free passage to 
families.—When 
a member of the Force is sent on detachment duty from the headquarters of the 
Force and the duration of the duty is expected to last for a period of not less 
than one month the Commandant may, if he considers it desirable that his family 
should not remain at headquarters, issue free railway warrant to the members of 
his family covering the journey from the headquarters to the railway station 
nearest to their home. This concession shall be admissible to all ranks of the 
Force except the Gazetted Officers.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>92</number> Free leave pass 
concessions.—The 
undermentioned free pass concessions from the Headquarters of the Force or the 
place of duty of the railway station nearest to his home and return shall be 
admissible to Head Constables, Naiks, Constables and enrolled followers of the 
Force:
 <section>
       <number>1</number> One free leave pass every three 
years.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> One free leave pass for family 
every six years.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> Free leave pass when proceeding 
on medical leave of duration of not less than one month, provided it is 
certified that the illness or injury, which necessitated medical leave was not 
brought about by any fault, or negligence on the part of the member of the 
Force concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>93</number> Dress regulations.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The Dress Regulations for officers and all ranks shall be as prescribed in this 
Chapter and as laid down in the Force Standing Orders. No additions or 
alterations to these Regulations may be made without the previous sanction of 
the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The colours of the 
Force shall be light blue and white, the distinctive colour being light blue.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>94</number> Superior officers.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Gazetted Officers of the Force shall be entitled to uniform grant as indicated 
below:
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number> Officers of the Regular Army or 
Police joining the Force on deputation as Gazetted Officers Rs. 200.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Local Promotees or directly 
recruited Gazetted Officers.
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number> Initial uniform grant of Rs. 
900 regulated as under:
 <subsubsubsection>
                  <number>i</number> Rs. 450 half of the 
grant after 3 months continuous officiating or temporary service in the 
gazetted rank in the Force and a certificate from the Inspector General of 
Police that the officer concerned is likely to continue as such.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                 <number>ii</number> Rs. 450 representing 
the balance on completion of three years’ service as gazetted officer in the 
Force or on confirmation, whichever is earlier, subject to the stipulation that 
the Officer concerned, if not substantive when the amount becomes due, is 
certified by the Inspector General of Police as fit for permanent retention in 
the Force.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>b</number> Renewal uniform grant of Rs. 
450 at intervals of every five years to be calculated in respect of temporary 
or officiating Gazetted Officers from the date they complete 3 months’ 
temporary or officiating service in the Central Reserve Police in a gazetted 
post.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> State Police or Army officers 
initially appointed on deputation but subsequently retained permanently in the 
Force:
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number> Initial uniform grant of Rs. 
900 (Rs. 450 intially, the amount of Rs. 200 paid to them as deputationists 
being deducted from this amount, the balance of Rs. 450 being paid after they 
have completed 3 years’ service thereafter).
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>b</number> Renewal uniform grant of Rs. 
450 every five years (to be reckoned from the date of confirmation in the 
Central Reserve Police Force.)
 
                 Note.—“The 
grant of initial uniform allowance mentioned in item (3) to the officers 
mentioned in the said item shall be subject to the condition that if the 
officer has availed of any initial or renewal grant from his parent Department 
or the State Government for any period extending beyond the date of his 
permanent absorption in the Central Reserve Police Force, the proportionate 
amount of the initial or renewal grant sanctioned by this Department or State 
shall be adjusted in the total amount of the initial grant admissible under 
clause (a) of item (3)”.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Police or army (Serving Officers 
who are received on deputation in the Central Reserve Police Force but get 
release or retirement whilst in the Force and are continued in the same rank in 
the Force (Rs. 200 if the period of their employment in the Central Reserve 
Police Force exceeds one year).
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number> Retired or Released officers 
re-employed in the Central Reserve Police (Rs. 200 if the period of their 
re-employment in the Central Reserve Police Force exceeds one year).
 
                 Notes.—1. 
“No offficer (whether he was appointed by direct recruitment or by promotion or 
was initially taken by way of deputation or re-employed and has subsequently 
been permanently absorbed in the Force) who is due to retire within two years 
of the date on which the grant of uniform allowance falls due shall be entitled 
to the grant of that allowance.”
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>2</number> An officer mentioned in 
item (2) or (3) quitting service on resignation or discharge within the period 
for which the grant is sanctioned shall be liable to refund the proportionate 
amount of the grant of uniform allowance.
 
The uniform of superior 
officers of the Force is that prescribed for officers of the Indian Police 
Service, with the undermentioned minor alterations to distinguish them as 
members of the Force. As and when Indian Police Service Officers are taken on 
deputation in the Force they shall be entitled to wear the same badges of rank 
which they are entitled to in the Indian Police Service.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>1</number> Shoulder Badges—A white Metal 
badge consisting of the letter C.R.P. in half inch block letters to be worn at 
the base of the shoulder strap.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number> Buttons—of white metal, convex in 
shape, die struck and embossed with the C.R.P. device in four sizes.
 
              The C.R.P. device for use on 
buttons will consist of a monogram of the letter C.R.P. surmounted by Ashoka 
Chakra.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number> Badges of rank—
 
              
Commandant                                     State emblem one star.
 
              Assistant Commandant (both 
Second-in           
Command and Adjutant)                      State emblem
 
              Company Commander, Quarter 
Master  
and Deputy Supdt. of Police (Radio       Three stars. 
officer)
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number> Badges and Metal Fittings—All 
Superior officers of the Force shall wear buttons, badges, and metal fittings 
of white metal.
 
              The star shall be of the star 
of Indian pattern.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number> Head Gear—Except in the case of 
Sikh officers who may wear Khaki pagree, head gear shall be Army regulation 
pattern with pith topee, fitted with two chin straps, one of which shall pass 
over the top of the helmet and shall be worn down when required. The topee 
shall have a pagree of nine folds of khaki with a light blue flash a quarter of 
an inch wide at the top between the helmet and the pagree, the whole when tied 
not to exceed three inches in width.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number> Ties—Superior officers shall wear 
a navy blue tie of regulation pattern.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>7</number>  (a) Swords—of the pattern 
prescribed for I.P./I.P.S. officers, except  
that Army officers may wear their own (Army) swords.
 </subsection></section><section>
              <number>b</number> The following 
modifications are permissible in the Dress uniform of superior officers for use 
on informal occasions:—
 <subsection>
            <number>1</number> Bush shirt—The pattern of 
the bush shirt shall be as for a jacket with the following modifications, no 
ties shall be worn with the bush shirt.
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>i</number> Button-up Collar, 
1-1/2 inches in width at back and 2-1/2 to 3 inches at points.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 <number>ii</number> Sleeves, as for a 
shirt with single plain cuff 2-1/4 inches in width and one button.
 <subsubsubsection>
 <number>N</number>B.—For hot 
weather, the sleeves may either be rolled up or short sleeves be worn.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 <number>iii</number> Four buttons 
excluding collar button, top button to be four inches below collar button and 
the remainder evenly spaced.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                <number>iv</number> Belt two inches broad 
with silver plated buckle to be made either of khaki drill or khaki twill.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 <number>v</number> All buttons to be of 
bone.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
            <number>2</number> Badges—Worsted Shoulder and 
rank badges on detachable shoulder straps.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>3</number> Forage Cap—khaki forage cap 
of darb material of regulation shade, with peak of same material, brown leather 
chin stray C.R.P. crest. The crest shall consist of a monogram of the letters 
C.R.P., followed by a wreath, with Ashoka Chakra on top.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>4</number> Shoes—Brown shoes, instead 
of ankle boots, may be worn with trousers.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>5</number> Breeches, boots and 
spurs—These articles shall not be worn except for mounted duties when specially 
ordered.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>c</number> Indian Police Service officers 
wearing state Emblem and two stars shall wear (i) a dark blue band of woollen 
material to be placed between the two lower welts of the forage cap with silver 
embroidered C.R.P. crest, and if wearing pugree, a similar blue band and 
embroidered crest on the pugree, and (ii) Gorget—patches of dark blue woollen 
material with a Central Silver stripe.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>95</number> Scale of uniform.—1[The 
authorised scale of uniform for subordinate officers and other ranks of the 
Force as well as enrolled followers shall be such as the Director General may, 
from time to time, and with the previous sanction of the Central Government, by 
order, law down.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>96</number> Initial issue and 
replacement of uniforms.—On 
enlistment a free issue of uniform shall be made to each subordinate officer, 
lower rank and enrolled follower according to the scale laid down 

1[under rule 95].
 
 




</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>97</number> Periodical 
Inspections.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Periodical inspections shall be held by Platoon Commanders at least once a 
month; at which articles which are no longer fit for use shall be condemned and 
sent to Stores for replacement.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If the life of a 
condemned article has expired, it shall be replaced free. If its life has not 
expired, the article shall be replaced and a proportionate cost deducted from 
the pay of the member of the Force concerned. A free issue may be sanctioned if 
the article has been rendered unserviceable owing to excessive wear and tear on 
duty or has been lost on duty through no fault of the member of the Force 
concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Condemned articles 
shall be utilised, where possible, for repair work, dusters, etc. 
Periodical public auctions of the remaining condemned articles shall be held 
and the sale proceeds credited to Government. A member of the Force may 
purchase condemned articles of clothing for his private use at price fixed by 
the Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> When a member of the 
Force ceases to belong to the Force, his kit shall be examined and serviceable 
articles brought on to the resumed stock and subsequently re-issued. When any 
such resumed article is re-issued, its life period shall count from the date of 
original issue and not from the date of re-issue.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> On promotion to the 
rank of Sub-Inspector an Under Officer shall be entitled to receive free 
initial supply of uniform as prescribed for Subordinate Officers, his Under 
Officer’s kit being returned to stores.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> All Under Officers 
and men shall deposit their uniform in the store when proceeding on leave, 
excepting such articles of clothing as may be permitted by the Commandant to be 
retained.
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> A superior officer or 
subordinate officer on his retirement or superannuation or invalidation may be 
allowed by the I.G.P. or Dy. I.G.P. as the case may be, to retain one suit of 
uniform provided his work and conduct has been found satisfactory. Such officer 
may wear the said uniform after such retirement with the permission of the 
I.G.P. or of the Dy. I.G.P. as the case may be, subject to such conditions as 
the I.G.P. or Dy. I.G.P. may think fit to impose.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>98</number> Uniform Stock 
Registers.—The 
Quarter Master shall maintain the following stock registers:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number> A uniform stock register in 
respect of all receipts of uniform for initial issue and replacement. All 
issues whether as initial issue or replacement shall be accounted for in this 
stock register.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> A Resume Stock Register in which 
shall be entered all transactions of uniform returned and re-issued.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number> A Condemned Stock Register in 
which shall be entered all receipts of uniform condemned and disposed of by 
sale or otherwise.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>99</number> Authorised scales.—The 
scale of equipment to be drawn from the regular Army Ordnance Corps shall be as 
sanctioned by the Government of India and shall be as shown in the “Equipment 
Tables (India) for Central Reserve Police, January 1945, issued by the 
Government of India in the then War Department” as subsequently amended from 
time to time.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>100</number> Accoutrements.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Accoutrements are those personal articles of equipment which are issued to men 
for their use and for the care of which they are personally responsible.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Accoutrements remains 
the property of the Government.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>101</number> Accoutrements of 
subordinate officers.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Swords and belts shall not be supplied to re-employed Commissioned Officers who 
are in possession of swords and Sam Browne belts of Infantry pattern.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Inspector General 
may as a reward for exemplary service sanction the retention of his sword and 
Sam Browne belt.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>102</number> Other conditions of 
service.—The 
conditions of service of members of the Force in respect of matters for which 
no provision is made in these rules shall be the same as are for the time being 
applicable to other officers of the Government of India of corresponding 
status.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>103</number> Cadre Regulations.—There 
shall be a separate cadre for the superior posts in the Force manned by Army or 
Indian Police Service or State Police Officers, direct recruits and local 
promotees. The strength of the cadre shall be flexible but ordinarily it shall, 
for a four-service Company Battalion, have such number of superior officers 
determined in accordance with the provisions of clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-rule (1) of 
rule 5.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>104</number> 
Classification.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The posts of Commandant, Assistant Commandant (Second-in Command/Adjutant) and 
Company Commander/Quarter Master shall be the posts included in the General 
Central Service, Class-I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The posts of 
Principal, Vice-Principal and Assistant Principal of the Central Training 
College, Central Reserve Police Force, Neemuch, shall also be the posts 
included in the General Central Service, Class-I.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>105</number> Appointment and 
promotion of superior officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The post of Commandant of a Battalion, other than Signal Battalion or 
Principal, CTC shall be filled:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> by transfer on deputation from 
the rank of Lt. Colonel from the Army or Indian Police Service (Senior Scale) 
Officers or State Police Officers holding posts of Superintendent of Police or 
equivalent posts, preferably with experience of Armed Police duties; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> by re-employment of retired or 
released Army Officers of Indian Police Service (Senior Scale) Officers or 
State Police Officers holding posts of Superintendent of Police or equivalent 
posts, preferably with experience of Armed Police duties of Commandants of the 
Central Reserve Police Force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  by promotion from amongst 
Assistant Commandant (Second-in Command/Adjutant/Junior Staff Officers, 
Vice-Principal, Central Training College) who have either served in the Force 
for a minimum period of two years or are otherwise eligible to be posted as 
Commandant under clause (i); or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> in cases not falling under 
clause (iii), by promotion from amongst the locally promoted and substantive 
Assistant Commandants (Second-in-Command/Adjutant/Junior Staff 
Officer/Vice-Principal, Central Training College).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The post of 
Commandant in the Signal battalion shall be filled:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> by transfer on deputation of 
officers having the required technical qualifications, from the rank of Lt. 
Colonel from the Army or Indian Police Service (Senior Scale) Officers of State 
Police Officers holding post of Superintendent of Police or equivalent posts, 
or those holding post of Deputy Superintendent of Police for a period of not 
less than eight years; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> by re-employment of officers 
having the required technical qualifications, from among retired/released Army 
Officers of the rank of Lt. Colonel or Indian Police Service (Senior Scale) 
Officers or State Police Officers of the rank of Superintendent of Police or 
equivalent posts of Central Reserve Police Force Officers of the Signal 
Battalion of the rank of Commandant; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> by promotion from amongst 
Assistant Commandants, having the required technical qualifications, who, if on 
deputation, have served in the Force for a minimum period of two years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3A</number> The posts of 
Assistant Commandants (Second-in Command or Adjutant or Junior Staff Officer or 
Vice-Principal, Central Training College) in Battalions other than Signals 
Battalion shall be filled:
 

         1[(i) by transfer on 
deputation from amongst officers:—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number> holding the rank of Major in 
the Army, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number> who are members of the 
Indian Police Service (Senior Scale), or have rendered four years of service as 
such, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>c</number> of the State Police holding 
the post of Superintendent of Police or equivalent post, preferably with 
experience of Armed Police duties, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>d</number> of the National Cadet Corps 
holding posts in the scale not lower than Rs. 1200-1700, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>e</number> of the Home Guards and Civil 
Defence Organisations holding posts in the scale of pay not lower than Rs. 
1200-1700.]
 <subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number> by re-employment of retired or 
released Army Officers or substantive Majors of the Territorial Army or Indian 
Police Service Officer (Senior scale) or with four years of service as such or 
State Police Officers holding the posts of Superintendent of Police or 
equivalent posts preferably with experience of Armed Police duties or Assistant 
Commandants of the Central Reserve Police Force; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number> by promotion:
 <subsubsubsection>
            <number>a</number> from amongst Assistant 
Superintendents of Police serving in the Central Reserve Police Force on 
deputation who have been promoted to the senior scale of the Indian Police 
Service or have completed four years of service in the Indian Police Service; 
or
 

                2[(b)  from amongst 
Company Commanders or Quarter Masters or Assistant Principals, Central Training 
College of the Central Reserve Police Force who have completed 5 years gazetted 
service in the force.]
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3B</number> The post of 
Assistant Commandant in the Signals Battalions shall be filled:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> by transfer on deputation of 
officers having the required technical qualifications, from the rank of Major 
from the Army or Indian Police Service Officers who have been promoted to the 
Senior Scale of the Indian Police Service or those who have completed four 
years of service in the Indian Police Service or State Police Officers holding 
posts of Superintendent of Police or equivalent posts, or these holding posts 
of Deputy Superintendent of Police for a period of not less than six years; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  by re-employment of officers 
having the required technical qualifications, from among retired/released Army 
Officers of the rank of Major substantive Major of the territorial Army or 
Indian Police Service Officers (Senior Scales) or State Police Officers of the 
rank of Superintendent of Police or equivalent posts of Central Reserve Police 
Force Officers of the Signals Battalions of the rank of Assistant Commandant; 
or
 

       3[(iii)  by promotion from 
amongst technically qualified Company Commanders/Quarter Masters or Assistant 
Principals, Central Training Colleges of the Central Reserve Police Force who 
have completed 5 years gazetted service in the Force;]
 

4[(3C) The posts 
of Assistant Commandant (Executive Engineer) in the Force shall be filled by:
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> promotion of Deputy 
Superintendent of Police (Assistant Engineer) in the Force with six years’ 
service in technical line; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> appointment of Assistant 
Commandants serving in the Force who have rendered 5 years’ service in the Army 
Engineering Corps and attended Young Officers Courses of Corps of Engineers at 
College of Military Engineering, Pune; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> transfer on deputation of 
officers holding analogous post of Deputy Superintendent of Police (Assistant 
Engineer) with 6 years’ service in technical line of Engineers, from other 
Central Police Organisations or Government Departments;]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The posts of Company 
Commander or Quarter Master in Battalions other than Signals Battalion or 
Assistant Principal, Central Training College shall be filled:
 

         5[(i)  by transfer on 
deputation of officers holding post of Captain in the Army or Assistant 
Superintendent of Police or Deputy Superintendent of Police in a State or an 
officer of the National Cadet Corps holding post in the scale of pay not lower 
than Rs. 700-1300 or officers of the Home Guards or Civil Defence Organisations 
holding posts in the scale of pay not lower than Rs. 700-1300.]
 <subsection>
        <number>ii</number> by promotion:
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> by transfer on deputation (by 
promotion) of Inspectors on the select list for promotion to the posts of 
Deputy Superintendent of Police or equivalent posts in the State Police or 
substantive holders of the posts of Inspector or equivalent posts or 
officiating Inspector with at least three years’ continuous service in that 
grade or equivalent posts in any Central or State Police Organisation 
preferably with the experience of Armed Police; or
 

                6[(a) by promotion of 
Subedars with a minimum service of 3 years in that rank in the Force, who have 
successfully completed the Senior Subedars’ Refresher Course, Central Reserve 
Police Force],
 

           7[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> by direct recruitment from 
amongst the candidates possessing the following qualifications, namely:—
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number> must have attained the age 
of 19 years and must not have attained the age of 25 years age limit being 
relaxable in the case of Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribes candidates and 
other special categories of persons in accordance with the orders issued by the 
Central Government from time to time.
 
                       Note.—1. 
Preference may be given to candidates possessing experience of the Armed 
Police, Territorial Army or other Armed Forces;
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
                  <number>2</number> 

8[The age limit of 25 years is 
relaxable for Government Servants upto 5 years in accordance with the 
instructions or orders issued by the Central Government.]
 

                 9[(b) (i) a first 
class or second class Bachelor’s degree of a recognised university;
 <subsection>
                 <number>ii</number>  a third class 
Bachelor’s degree plus National Cadet Corps ‘B’ Certificate or ‘C’ certificate 
or outstanding sport or athletic certificates; or
 </subsection><subsection>
                 <number>iii</number> a degree in 
Tele-Communication Engineering of a recognised university;
 <subsubsection>
            <number>c</number> must satisfy the minimum 
physical standards, namely; height 165 Cms; chest 81 Cms. (unexpanded) 86 Cms. 
(expanded); weight 50 Kgs; eyes sight (with or without glasses) distant vision 
6/6 in one eye and 6/9 in the other eye; near vision 0.6 in one eye and 0.8 in 
the other eye; candidates should not have knock knees or flat foot;
 

           10[(cc)  in the case of 
female candidates, they must satisfy physical standard, namely—height 157 Cms; 
weight according to height but not less than 46 kgs; eye sight (with or without 
glasses) distant vision 6/6 in one eye and 6/9 in the other eye; near vision 
0.6 in one eye and 0.8 in the other eye, candidates should not have knock knee 
or flat foot;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>d</number> must possess all other 
qualifications as may be prescribed by the Central Government from time to time 
regarding citizenship, eligibility and such other matters; or
 <subsubsubsection>
     <number>ivA</number> by appointment of emergency 
Commissioned Officers and short-service Commissioned Officers of the Armed 
Forces of the Union who were commissioned on or after the 1st November, 1962 
and were released at any time thereafter;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number> by re-employment of retired or 
released Army Officers who have held the rank of Captain or retired Police 
Officers or Officers of the Force who have held the rank of a Deputy 
Superintendent of Police or other equivalent ranks.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4A</number> The posts of Company 
Commander in the Signals Battalions shall be filled:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> by transfer on deputation of 
officers having the required technical qualification from the rank of Captain 
of the Army or Assistant Superintendent of Police or Deputy Superintendent of 
Police in a State; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> by transfer on deputation (by 
promotion) of officers having the required technical qualifications from 
amongst Inspectors on the select list for promotion to the posts of Deputy 
Superintendent of Police or equivalent posts in a State Police or substantive 
holders of the post of Inspector or equivalent posts of officiating Inspectors 
with at least three years’ continuous service in that grade or equivalent posts 
in any Central or State Organisation, preferably with the experience of Armed 
Police;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> by promotion from amongst 
technically qualified Subedars below the age of 50 years and with minimum 
service of three years in that rank, in the Central Reserve Police Force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> by direct recruitment from 
amongst technically qualified candidates possessing the additional 
qualifications as prescribed in clause (iv) of sub-rule (4); or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number> by re-employment of technically 
qualified and retired or released Army Officers who held the rank of Captain or 
retired State Police Officer or officers of the Force who have held the rank of 
a Deputy Superintendent of Police or equivalent ranks.
 

11[(4B) For the 
purposes of sub-rules (4) and (4A) the percentage for recruitment shall be as 
follows:
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> by direct 
recruitment                50%
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> by 
promotion                           50%
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> any shortfall in direct 
recruitment or recruitment by promotion in the rank of Deputy Superintendent of 
Police may be filled by deputation or re-employment as specified in these 
rules.]
 

12[(4C) The posts 
of Deputy Superintendent of Police (Assistant Engineer) shall be filled by:
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> promotion of Serving Inspector 
(Overseer) with 3 years’ service as such in the Force and haing degree/diploma 
in Civil Engineering; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> Serving Deputy Superintendent 
of Police with 3 years commissioned service in Army Corps of Engineers and who 
has attended Young Officer’s Course of Corps of Engineers at College of 
Military Engineering, Pune or Serving Deputy Superintendent of Police in the 
Force with degree in Civil Engineering; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  transfer on deputation of 
officers holding analogous post from other Central Police Organisations or 
Government Department.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> All promotions shall 
be on the basis of merit with due regard to seniority.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the Central 
Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it 
may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax any of the 
provisions of this rule with respect to any class or category of persons.
 
 















</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>106</number> Training.—
<section><number>i</number> 
The officers received on deputation from the Army and Police Forces of States 
may be required to undergo a short course of training as prescribed to enable 
them to acquire working knowledge of the Central Reserve Police Force before 
they are finally posted to take up their appointments.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Direct recruits 
shall be required to undergo a full course of instruction at a Training Centre 
for Public Officers.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>107</number> Tenure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The initial period of appointment of all officers on deputation whether 
belonging to the Police or the Army, shall not be less than three years, 
subject to premature termination, should 
<subsection><number>a</number> administrative exigency or (b) 
unsuitability of the officers concerned or (c) any other unforeseen factors so 
demand. This initial period shall be extendable, on a yearly basis, on mutual 
agreement between the officer concerned and the lending and the borrowing 
authorities, provided that the total period of appointment in the Force shall 
not be more than 5 years, unless the officer is permanently absorbed in the 
Force.
 

1[(2) (a) In the 
case of officers re-employed after they had retired/discharged/released from 
Army prior to the attainment of the age of superannuation in the civil posts 
will, if appointed to civil posts, be treated as direct recruits and their 
seniority in the grade fixed accordingly as under:
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number> the inter-se seniority of 
persons so re-employed shall be determined in accordance with the orders of 
their selection;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number> the relative seniority of 
persons so re-employed in relation to direct recruits and promotees shall be 
determined on the basis of chronology of selection;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number> their confirmation and 
promotion to higher posts would take place with reference to seniority so fixed 
subject to fulfilment of other laid down conditions regarding probation.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The ex-army officers 
re-employed after they have attained the age of superannuation in civil posts 
shall not form part of the cadre and would be treated as if appointed on 
contract basis and such re-employments on contract basis shall be extendable on 
year to year basis.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>108</number> Probation and 
confirmation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The selected candidates shall be appointed or promoted to a superior post in 
the Force on probation for a period of two years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the completion of 
the period of probation, the candidates shall, if considered fit for permanent 
appointment, be confirmed in their appointments subject to the availability of 
substantive vacancies in permanent posts.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Government may 
extend the period of two years specified in sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If on the expiration 
of the period of probation referred to in sub-rule (1) or of any extension 
thereof under sub-rule (3), as the case may be, the Government are of the 
opinion that a candidate if not fit for permanent appointment, or if at any 
time during such period of probation or extension they are satisfied that he 
will not be fit for permanent appointment on the expiration of such period of 
probation on extension, they may discharge him or pass such orders as they 
think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no action is 
taken by Government under sub-rule (2) or (3) or (4), the period after the 
prescribed period of probation shall be treated as an engagement from month to 
month terminable on either side on the expiration of one calendar month’s 
notice in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A probationer may be 
required to pass such tests as may be prescribed including a test in Hindi 
before confirmation.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> On promotion to a 
superior post in the Force, the officiating service in that post or an 
equivalent post previously rendered may be allowed to count towards the 
probationary period at the discretion of the controlling authority.
 
Note.—“Controlling 
authority” for the purpose of this rule will be the Inspector General of 
Police, Central Reserve Police.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>109</number> Transfers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In any Battalion, Company Commanders and Quarter Masters may be transferred 
from one Company to another Company by the Deputy Inspector-General with due 
intimation to the Inspector-General of Police.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Superior Officers 
from one Battalion to another Battalion may be transferred by the 
Inspector-General of Police with due intimation to the Central Government.
</section></article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>110</number> Discipline and 
Appeal.—The 
Superior Officers of the Force shall be subject to the provisions of the 
Central Civil Service (Classifications, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1957, as 
amended from time to time.
</article> 
 
The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 
RULES, 1955
 
 
 <article>
<number>111</number> Pensions and 
Pensionary Benefits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provision of sub-rule (2) Superior Officers of the Force shall 
be entitled to such pension and pensionary benefits as are admissible under the 
rules applicable to the service to which they belong.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On his permanent 
transfer to the Force, or within six months thereafter the officer may elect to 
be governed by the Liberalised Pension Rules, 1950 as amended from time to 
time. The options once exercised shall be final and will be communicated by the 
officer to the audit in writing with a copy to the appointing authority within 
the said period of six months. If no such election is made, he will 
automatically be governed by the said rules.
 
Note.—The 
Superior Officers who have already been absorbed in the Force and have not yet 
exercised the option, may do so within six months hereafter, failing which they 
will automatically be governed by the said rules.
</section></article><form>
 


The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 

RULES, 1955
 


 
 



1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Appendix A omitted by G.S.R. 244, 
dated 27th March, 1989 (w.e.f. 8-4-1989).
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The CENTRAL RESERVE POLICE FORCE
 

RULES, 1955
 


 
 


APPENDIX “C”
 


(See rule 9)
 


OATH OR AFFIRMATION TO BE TAKEN ON 
ATTESTATION
 


(a) The oath or affirmation to be taken on 
attestation shall be in one of the forms or in such other form to the same 
purport as the Attestation Officer ascertain to be in accordance with the 
religion of the member of the Force to be attested, or otherwise binding on his 
conscience.
 


FORM OF OATH
 


I,............... swear by Almighty God that 
I shall be faithful and bear true allegiance to India and to the Constitution 
of India as by law established and that I shall as in duty bound, honestly and 
faithfully serve in the Central Reserve Police Force and go wherever I may be 
ordered by air, land or sea, and that I shall observe and obey all commands of 
any Officer set over me even to the peril of my life.
 


FORM OF AFFIRMATION
 


I,............... solemnly affirm in the 
presence of Almighty God that I shall be faithful and bear true allegiance to 
India and to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I shall 
as in duty bound, honestly and faithfully serve in the Central Reserve Police 
Force and go wherever I may be ordered by air, land or sea, and that I shall 
observe and obey all commands of any officer set over me even to the peril of 
my life.
 


(b) The oath or affirmation prescribed, 
shall whenever practicable, be administered by the Commandant.
 


(c) The following is a translation into 
Hindi of the above affirmation:—
 


Main...................Parmeshwar ko sakshi 
manker apne dharm se paran karta hun ke main Hindustan aur Hindustan ki hakumat 
jo ke kanun se banai gai hai ka sachche man se hiteshi rahunga aur Central 
Reserve Police Force men apne dharm aur sachchai ke sath sewa karata rahunga, 
Pawan, Jal, Bhumi me se jis marg se jane ki agya hogi jaunga, aur jise mera 
adhikari sthapit kiya jaega uski sari agyaon ki tan man se palan karunga yadi 
usmen pran jane ka bhi bhay ho.
 


THE OATH FOR SIKHS BEGINS
 


Main............ Shri Guru Granth Sahibji ki 
saugandh khaker kahta hun ki main..............(and proceeds as in the Hindi 
translation of the form of affirmation).
 


THE OATH FOR MUSLIMS BEGINS
 


Main.................khuda-i-Taala ko 
hazir-o-nazir jankar iman se eqrar karta hun ki main Hindustan aur Hindustan ki 
hakumat jo ki kanun se banai gai hai ka sachche dil se wafadar rahunga aur 
Central Reserve Police Force men imandari se faraz shinasi se khidmat ka faraz 
baja launga, Hawa, khuski ya tari ke raste jahan bhi jane ka hukam milega, 
jaunga aur jise mera officer muqarrar kiya jaega uske sub hukam ki tamil aur 
pairwi karunga khwa us men jan ka kahtra ho.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
Rule 38 deleted by G.S.R. 605, dated 18th April, 1961.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 480, dated 21st 
March, 1977.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Rule 49 omitted by G.S.R. 165, dated 
17th May, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 1391, dated 5th 
October, 1979.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 62, dated 31st 
December, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Added by G.S.R. 1242, dated 14th 
September, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 877, dated 3rd 
October, 1981.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 527, dated 6th June, 
1981.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Added by G.S.R. 527, dated 21st May, 
1981.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Added by G.S.R. 527, dated 21st May, 
1981.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 280, dated 6th 
February, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 291(E), dated 22nd 
April, 2004 (w.e.f. 28-4-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 285, dated 4th 
December, 1992 (w.e.f. 26-12-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 235, dated 15th 
February, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 421, dated 19th 
April, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 244, dated 27th 
March, 1989 (w.e.f. 8-4-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 244, dated 27th 
March, 1989 (w.e.f. 8-4-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 1241, dated 24th 
June, 1968.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 569, dated 18th July, 
1986.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 943, dated 20th 
September, 1985.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>