<act><title>


The Electricity (Procedure for Previous 
    Publication) Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules shall be called the Electricity (Procedure for Previous Publication) 
    Rules, 2005.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These 
    rules shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette. 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise, requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the words and expressions used and not 
    defined herein but defined in the Act shall have the meaning assigned to 
    them in the Act.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Procedure of previous publication.—For 
    the purpose of previous publication of regulations under sub-section (3) of 
    section 177, sub-section (3) of section 178 and sub-section (3) of section 
    181 of the Act, the following procedure shall apply:—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>    the Authority or the Appropriate 
    Commission shall, before making regulations, publish a draft of the 
    regulations for the information of persons likely to be affected thereby;  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    the publication shall be made in such 
    manner as the Authority or the Appropriate Commission deems to be 
    sufficient;  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    there shall be published with the draft 
    regulations, a notice specifying a date on or after which the draft 
    regulations will be taken into consideration;  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    the Authority or the Appropriate 
    Commission having powers to make regulations shall consider any objection or 
    suggestion which may be received by the Authority or the Appropriate 
    Commission from any person with respect to the draft before the date so 
    specified.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> 
      The publication in the Official Gazette of the regulations made in 
      exercise of a power to make regulations after previous publication shall 
      be conclusive proof that the regulations have been duly made.  
  
  
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>