<act><tid>1298776</tid>
<title>THE MURSHIDABAD ESTATE ADMINISTRATION ACT, <year>1933</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1933</year>
[ 21st September, <year>1933</year>.]

AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE APPOINTMENT OF A MANAGER ON BEHALF 
OF THESECRETARY





<article><tid>463416</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>270231</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Murshidabad Estate Administration Act, <year>1933</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1181171</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories which 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part 
States].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1698761</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in 
the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1568726</tid>
<number>1</number>immoveable properties of the estate" means the 
properties contained in the Schedules of immoveable 
property annexed to the Indenture included in and 
confirmed by the Murshidabad Act, <year>1891</year>, (15 of <year>1891</year>.) 
with any additional immoveable property added thereto 
under sub- section (1) of section 3 of that Act, and 
includes all immoveable property acquire under the 
provisions of section 32 of the Land Acquisition Act, 
 <year>1894</year>; (1 of <year>1894</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>438209</tid>
<number>2</number>issues and profits of the immoveable properties of 
the estate" includes all money awarded under the Land 
Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year>, (1 of <year>1894</year>.) as compensation for 
the acquisition of any of the immoveable properties of 
the estate together with interest thereon;

</section>

<section><tid>1016216</tid>
<number>3</number>" Manager" means the officer appointed under 
section 3

</section>

<section><tid>686949</tid>
<number>4</number>" Nawab Bahadur" means the Nawab Bahadur of 
Murshidabad for the time being;
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 
 (6)" Board of Revenue" means the Board of Revenue, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> West Bengal]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" Bengal

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Cl. (5) Omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

thirdly. so long as such management continues-


<subsection><tid>1546029</tid>
<number>a</number>the Nawab Bahadur shall be incompetent to mortgage, 
charge, lease, settle or alienate the immoveable 
properties of the estate, or to grant valid receipts for 
the rents and profits arising or accruing therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>792466</tid>
<number>b</number>such property shall be exempt from attachment or 
sale under process of any Court; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>642629</tid>
<number>c</number>the Nawab Bahadur shall be incapable of entering into 
any contract which may involve him in pecuniary 
liability; and
fourthly, any amount awarded, before the entry <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of the 
State Government] upon the immovable properties of the 
estate, under the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year>, (1 of  
  <year>1894</year>.) by way of compensation for immoveable properties 
of the estate acquired under that Act, if the amount has 
been invested in securities under section 32 of that Act 
or is deposited in Court pending such investment in land 
or securities, shall, together with all interest and 
other proceeds thereof not already paid to any person 
under the provisions of any law, be deliverable to the 
Manager on behalf <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of the State Government] to be 
disposed of in such manner as the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State Government] 
may think fit.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1208412</tid>
<number> 5</number> Suits and appeals during managements. So long as the 
appointment of the Manager continues-
<section><tid>933867</tid>
<number>1</number>in every suit or appeal to which <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
the State of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> West Bengal]] in possession is a party 
the Manager shall be named as' <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> its representative] for 
the purpose of such suit or appeal;

</section>

<section><tid>432293</tid>
<number>2</number>in every pending suit or appeal concerning the 
properties under management <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the State of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> West 
Bengal] 1 in possession shall be a party in place of the 
Nawab Bahadur and the Manager shall be named as the 
representative of <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the State of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> West Bengal]] in 
possession for the purpose of the suit or appeal; and 
no application in any such suit or appeal shall be made 
to the Court on behalf of <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the State of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> West Bengal] 
] in possession except by the Manager;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" of the Secretary of State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" Secretary of State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" the Secretary of State or" omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" Bengal

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs., ibid., for" his representative".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Secretary of State


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1683475</tid>
<number>3</number>the Court upon application by the Manager or by 
any party to the suit may order that the plaint or 
memorandum of appeal be amended so as to conform with 
the requirements of clause (1) or that the Manager be 
named as the representative of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State of West 
Bengal] in possession as required by clause (2) of this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>952498</tid>
<number> 6</number> Manager to receive rents. issues and profits.
<section><tid>1846031</tid>
<number>1</number>The Manager  
shall receive and recover all rents, issues and profits due in respect 
of the immoveable properties of the estate, and shall upon receiving 
such rents, issues and profits give receipts therefor.

</section>

<section><tid>630737</tid>
<number>2</number>The Manager shall receive the monthly sum of Rs. 19, 166- 10- 3 
payable from the Government Treasury at Berhampore in the district of 
Murshidabad in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> West Bengal] and shall give receipts therefor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>390788</tid>
<number> 7</number> Application by Manager of sums received.
<section><tid>601594</tid>
<number>1</number>From the sums  
received under sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 6, the Manager 
shall pay-
first, to the Nawab Bahadur such monthly sum, not being 
in any case less than Rs. 9, 583- 5- 4, as the State 
Government may fix in this behalf;

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> secondly, the allowances, if any, payable under 
section 3 of the Murshidabad Act, <year>1946</year>];

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> thirdly], the Government revenue, cesses, rates and 
taxes and all debts and liabilities for the time being 
due or incurred to Government or to any local authority;

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> fourthly], in the case of property held by the Nawab 
Bahadur as tenant, the rent and cess due to the superior 
landlord in respect of the said property;

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> fifthly], the cost of such repairs and improvements of 
the immoveable properties of the estate as appear 
necessary to the Manager and are approved by the Board 
of Revenue;

and shall apply the residue to the discharge of the costs of the 
management, to the payment of expenditure incurred in litigation and 
to the settlement in accordance with the scheme approved by the Board 
of Revenue under section 14 of such debts and liabilities of the Nawab 
Bahadur as may be established under the provisions of this Act.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" Secretary of State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Bengal".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Bengal Act 15 of <year>1946</year>, s. 5.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" secondly."

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs., ibid., for" thirdly".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs., ibid., for" fourthly


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>269443</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), it 
shall be lawful for the Manager to pay out of the sums received under 
subsections (1) and (2) of section 6 any sum required to meet such 
expenditure on any other object or for any other purpose as the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may from time to time sanction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>737994</tid>
<number>8</number>Notice to claimants. As soon as may be after the publication of 
the order for the appointment of a Manager under section 3 the Manager 
shall publish in the prescribed manner a notice in English and Bengali 
calling upon all persons having claims against the Nawab Bahadur to 
notify such claims in writing to the Manager within six months from 
the date of the notice.


</article>



<article><tid>899014</tid>
<number>9</number>Presentation of claims. Every such claimant shall, along with 
his claim, present to the Manager full particulars thereof, together 
with all documents on which he relies in support thereof, and the 
Manager may refuse to receive in evidence on the claimant' s behalf at 
the investigation of the claim any document not so presented.


</article>



<article><tid>1535741</tid>
<number>10</number>Debt not duly notified to barred. Every debt or liability, 
except debts due or liabilities incurred to the Government or to any 
local authority and rent due to a superior landlord from the Nawab 
Bahadur as tenant of any property, which is not duly notified to the 
Manager within the time and in the manner mentioned in sections 8 and 
 9 shall be barred:
Provided that if the Manager is satisfied that the claimant was 
for reasonable cause unable to comply with the provisions of sections 
 8 and 9, the Manager may admit his claim within a further period of 
six months from the expiration of the period of six months specified 
in section 8.



</article>



<article><tid>399523</tid>
<number>11</number>Determination of debts. The Manager shall in the prescribed 
manner determine the amount of the principal of all debts and 
liabilities not barred under section 10 justly due to the several 
creditors of the Nawab Bahadur and to persons holding mortgages, 
charges or liens on the property of the Nawab Bahadur, and shall 
determine in like manner the interest, if any, due at the date of such 
determination in respect of such debts and liabilities and may reduce 
the rates of interest charged as appears to him just and proper.


</article>



<article><tid>1778981</tid>
<number>12</number>Power to inquire into consideration for leases, etc. The 
Manager may inquire into the sufficiency of the consideration for 
which any lease, settlement, grant, mortgage, charge or lien was given 
and whether it was given in contravention of the conditions of the 
Murshidabad Act, <year>1891</year>, (15 of <year>1891</year>.) and if satisfied that the con- 
sideration was insufficient or that such lease, settlement, grant,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Secretary of State".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

mortgage, charge or lien was given in contravention of the said Act 
may, by order in writing, set aside or modify such lease, settlement, 
grant, mortgage, charge or lien; and any such order, subject to the 
appeal provided in section 13, shall have the force of a decree of a 
competent Civil Court and be enforceable as such.



</article>



<article><tid>453191</tid>
<number> 13</number> Appeals to Board of Revenue.
<section><tid>1781690</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the  
Board of Revenue against any order by the Manager-

<subsection><tid>1981170</tid>
<number>a</number>refusing to receive a document under section 9; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747109</tid>
<number>b</number>refusing to admit a claim under the proviso to 
section 10; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1729742</tid>
<number>c</number>determining the amount of a debt or liability or 
of interest thereon, or reducing the rate of 
interest, under section 11 or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1443021</tid>
<number>d</number>setting aside or modifying a lease, settlement, 
grant, mortgage. charge or lien under section 12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1092723</tid>
<number>2</number>If no such. appeal is preferred within six weeks from the 
date of the order, the decision of the Manager shall, subject to the 
provisions of section 22, be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500630</tid>
<number> 14</number> Scheme for settlement of debts.
<section><tid>1587453</tid>
<number>1</number>When the amount due in  
respect of the debts and liabilities mentioned in section 11 has been 
finally determined, the Manager shall prepare and submit to the Board 
of Revenue a schedule of such debts and liabilities, and a scheme for 
the settlement thereof in whole or in part out of the residue referred 
to in section 7 annually available during the lifetime of the Nawab 
Bahadur; and the Board of Revenue may approve the scheme without 
modification or subject to such modification as it deems expedient.

</section>

<section><tid>1665430</tid>
<number>2</number>The scheme shall provide for payment in full, as soon as may 
be, of-

<subsection><tid>1289510</tid>
<number>a</number>first, arrears of wages due to servants of the 
Nawab Bahadur, determined in accordance with the 
forgoing provisions, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1744088</tid>
<number>b</number>secondly, claims of each creditor whose claims in 
the aggregate do not exceed five hundred rupees, as so 
determined;
and the scheme shall further provide that any balance left after meet- 
ing the above claims and each annual residue thereafter shall be dis- 
tributed rateably among the other creditors of the Nawab Bahadur in 
payment of their claims, as so determined.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1282648</tid>
<number>15</number>Power to call for further particulars. The Manager may from 
time to time call for further and more detailed particulars of any 
claim preferred before him under this Act and may at his discretion 
refuse to proceed with the investigation of the claim until such 
particulars are supplied.



</article>



<article><tid>1841964</tid>
<number>16</number>Power to summon witnesses. The Manager may for the purpose of 
any investigation under this Act summon and enforce the attendance of 
witnesses and compel them to give evidence, and compel the production 
of documents, by the same means and as far as possible in the same 
manner as is provided in the case of a Civil Court by the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>. (5 of <year>1908</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>224075</tid>
<number>17</number>Investigation to be deemed a judicial proceeding. Every 
investigation conducted by the Manager with reference to any claim 
preferred before him under this Act, or to any matter connected with 
such claim, shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the 
meaning of the Indian Penal Code; (45 of <year>1860</year>.) and every statement 
made by any person examined by or before the Manager with reference to 
any such investigation, whether upon oath or otherwise, shall be 
deemed to be evidence within the meaning of the said Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1069902</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to order production of accounts, papers, etc., and 
evidence of title.
<section><tid>410316</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector of Murshidabad may on the  
application of the Manager order all persons who are or were in the 
employ of the estate of the Nawab Bahadur to attend before him; and 
may order any person to deliver up any accounts, papers or moveable 
property belonging to the estate or any accounts or papers relating to 
the immoveable property of the estate or to any other property of the 
estate which the Manager has reason to believe are in such person' s 
possession or control; and may order all holders of tenures or under- 
tenures on any such property to produce their titles to such tenures 
or undertenures.

</section>

<section><tid>1121646</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who refuses to comply with an order under sub- 
section (1) may be punished by the Collector of Murshidabad with fine 
not exceeding five hundred rupees:
Provided that an appeal shall lie to the Board of Revenue against 
any order of fine passed by the Collector under sub- section (2).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235829</tid>
<number> 19</number> Powers of Manager for realisation of rents, etc.
<section><tid>155207</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Manager shall have, for the purpose of realising and recovering the 
rents, issues and profits of the immoveable properties of the estate, 
the same powers as the Nawab Bahadur would have had for such purpose 
had the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] not entered into the said properties, and 
all arrears of rent and all demands recoverable as rent, and all 
interest due on such arrears or demands shall together with all costs 
incurred for realising the same be recoverable as public demands.

</section>

<section><tid>456331</tid>
<number>2</number>If such properties or any part thereof be in the possession 
of any mortgagee or conditional vendee, the Manager may apply to the 
Collector within whose jurisdiction the property is situated, and the 
Collector shall cause the same to be delivered to the Manager as if a 
decree therefor had been made in his favour, but without prejudice

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Secretary of State".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

to the mortgagee or vendee preferring his claim under the provisions 
elsewhere contained in this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>295030</tid>
<number>3</number>If such properties or any part thereof be in possession of a 
Receiver appointed by a Court, the Manager may apply to the Court, and 
the Court shall cause the same to be delivered to the Manager together 
with any receipts which may be in the hands of the Receiver or the 
Court at the time of the application.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1226194</tid>
<number>20</number>Powers to lease. The Manager may, subject to the prescribed 
conditions, make settlement of all or any of the immoveable properties 
of the estate and may for this purpose execute any lease or 
counterpart of a lease:
Provided that, unless the settlement is of a kind authorised by 
rule made under section 28, its terms and conditions shall have been 
previously approved by the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1449293</tid>
<number>21</number>Power of Manager to contract and take action for the benefit 
of the estate. The Manager may enter into any contract or take any 
action which in his opinion is necessary for the proper care and 
management of the immoveable properties of the estate and of the 
rents, issues and profits thereof or for the maintenance of the 
position and dignity of the Nawab Bahadur and which is not 
inconsistent with any provision of this Act or with any rule made 
under section 28:
Provided that if he is not empowered by any other provision of 
this Act or by any rule made under section 28 to enter on such con- 
tract or to take such action he shall obtain the previous sanction of 
the Board of Revenue before entering upon the contract or taking the 
action.



</article>



<article><tid>419659</tid>
<number> 22</number> Powers of supervision and control.
<section><tid>833968</tid>
<number>1</number>All orders or  
proceedings of the Manager in the exercise of his functions under this 
Act shall be subject to the supervision and control of the Board of 
Revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>240747</tid>
<number>2</number>All orders or proceedings of the Board of Revenue under this 
Act shall be subject to the supervision and control of the State Gov- 
ernment.

</section>

<section><tid>723195</tid>
<number>3</number>The supervising authority in each case may of its own motion 
review and if it thinks fit revise, modify or reverse any order of 
proceeding.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>175908</tid>
<number>23</number>Manager to be deemed a public servant. The Manager shall be 
deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>955158</tid>
<number>24</number>Recovery of fines. Any fine imposed under this Act shall be 
recoverable as a public demand.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1926605</tid>
<number>25</number>Bar of suits, etc., against certain persons. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against any person in respect of anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>954303</tid>
<number>26</number>Power of State Government to make orders. If at the time of the 
withdrawal of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] from entry upon the immoveable 
properties of the estate, any difficulty arises in connection with the 
restoration to the Nawab Bahadur or to his successor of the properties 
and rights possessed and exercised by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government], the 
State Government may by order authorise the doing of any matter or 
thing which appears to it necessary to facilitate such restoration.


</article>



<article><tid>1008884</tid>
<number>27</number>Effect of withdrawal from entry by State Government. 
Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this or any other Act, 
the withdrawal by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] from entry upon the 
immoveable properties of the estate shall not have the effect of 
reviving any of the proceedings referred to in clause first of section 
 4 if the debt or liability in respect of which such proceedings were 
instituted is barred under section 10.
Nothing in section 4 shall bar the revival after such withdrawal 
of any other of the proceedings referred to in the said clause:

Provided that no Court shall entertain any suit or proceeding 
against the Nawab Bahadur in which the amount claimed is in excess of 
the amount determined under section 11, 13 or 22, as the case may be, 
together with any further interest due thereon, or in which interest 
is claimed at a rate higher than the rate determined as just and 
proper under those sections.



</article>



<article><tid>1521020</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>70875</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board of Revenue may, with the  
previous sanction of the State Government make rules for the purpose 
of carrying into effect all or any of the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1326608</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the follow- 
ing matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>715865</tid>
<number>a</number>the security to be required from subordinate 
officers under Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656490</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure to be followed by the Manager in the 
discharge of his functions under this Act, the accounts 
which shall be kept by him, and the manner in which such 
accounts shall be audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>167908</tid>
<number>c</number>the terms, conditions and limitations under which 
leases may be granted;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Secretary of State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>926463</tid>
<number>d</number>the notices to be given under this Act and the 
manner of publication of such notices;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1924081</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure to be followed by claimants in 
presenting claims, and by the Manager in the 
investigation of such claims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>109287</tid>
<number>f</number>the procedure to be followed in determining under 
section 11 the debts and liabilities due to creditors 
and other persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1339982</tid>
<number>g</number>the allowance of interest on the principal of each 
of the debts and liabilities as determined under section 
 11 from the date on which it was incurred to the date of 
the determination and on the aggregate amount of such 
debts and liabilities from the date of the determination 
to the date of payment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43570</tid>
<number>h</number>the preparation of the schedule of debts and 
liabilities and of the scheme referred to in section 14 
and the order of payment of such debts and liabilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1862712</tid>
<number>i</number>the powers of the Manager to make or sanction 
settlements; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472000</tid>
<number>j</number>the procedure to be followed in appeals under this 
Act.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>